<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>jasonpbecker</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/feeds/education-policy-and-politics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.jsonbecker.com/</id><updated>2012-11-20T10:17:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>A little knowledge is a wonderful (dangerous) thing</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/11/a-little-knowledge-is-a-wonderful-dangerous-thing.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-11-20T10:17:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-11-20:2012/11/a-little-knowledge-is-a-wonderful-dangerous-thing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is so tempting to try to apply cognitive science results in education. It seems like an obvious step on the long road of moving education from a field of theory and philosophies to one more grounded in empirical research. Yet, learning myths are persistent. Even scarier, "&lt;a href="http://cedarsdigest.wordpress.com/2012/11/18/myths-come-from-values-not-from-ignorance/"&gt;those who know the most about neuroscience also believe the most myths.&lt;/a&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Educators may have the best intentions when trying to infuse their practice with evidence, but they all too often are not equipped as critical consumers of research. Worse, the education profession has historically been wrapped in "thoughtworld" &lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, where schools of education have taught same ideas about effective teaching and learning for decades without a basis in empirical research. These same ideas are taught to principals, district administrators, and teachers, so nary a critical voice can stop the myths from being repeated and mutually reinforcing each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectively conducting empirical research, translating research for policymakers, and implementing research-based program design is my job. I came to education purely from a research and policy perspective, and I am equipped to understand some of the empirical research done on effective schooling &lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to confront an awful history of "outsiders" like myself who have brought round after round of poorly supported, poorly evaluated reforms. I have to confront the history of districts and schools discarding some very effective programs because of leadership changes, lack of resources, and most of all a lack good, systematic evaluation of programs. And I have to be damn good at what I do, because even a small misstep could paint me just like every other "expert" that has rolled through with the newest great idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is why I tend to favor interventions that are very small. Simple, small, hard to "mess up" interventions,  based in research, implemented just a few at a time have tremendous potential. I love the oft-cited work on &lt;a href="http://www.nber.org/papers/w15361"&gt;filling out the FAFSA along with tax filing at H&amp;amp;R Block&lt;/a&gt;. It is simple. There is no fear of "dosage" or implementation fidelity. There are both sound theoretical reasons and empirical results from other domains that suggest a high likelihood of success. It has the potential to make a huge impact on students without adding any load to teachers who are, say, implementing a brand new and complicated curriculum this year. This is how you earn trust through building
success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also a fan of some really big, dramatic changes, but how I get there will have to be the subject of a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.D. Hirsch's term&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the area of neuroscience and cognitive science, I am probably only marginally better off than most teachers. My Sc.B. is in chemistry. So a background in empirical physical sciences and my knowledge of social science may help me to access some of the research on how people learn, but I would probably be just as susceptible to overconfidence in my ability to process this research and repeat untruths as many very intelligent educators.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="edpolicy"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="education policy"></category><category term="research"></category></entry><entry><title>Follow up to Nesi's Notes Guest Post: Woonsocket School Funding</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/07/follow-up-to-nesis-notes-guest-post-woonsocket-school-funding.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-07-12T09:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-07-12:2012/07/follow-up-to-nesis-notes-guest-post-woonsocket-school-funding.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/#!/tednesi"&gt;Ted Nesi&lt;/a&gt; was gracious in offering me a &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/?p=62059"&gt;guest spot on his blog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/category/nesis-notes/"&gt;Nesi's Notes&lt;/a&gt; this week to discuss education funding in Woonsocket. The main conclusions of my post are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​1. Woonsocket has not increased local funding for education over the last fifteen years despite massive increases in education expenditures in Rhode Island and nationwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​2. General education aid from the state has rapidly increased over the same period, demonstrating that a lack of sufficient revenue at Woonsocket Public Schools is first, if not exclusively, a local revenue
problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to provide three additional bits of information on my personal
blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/07/limitations-of-the-nesis-notes-analysis-and-some-additional-questions.html"&gt;First&lt;/a&gt;, I want to outline some analyses that I have not done that I think are critical to understanding education funding in Woonsocket. I will also describe more completely what conclusions cannot be drawn from
the analysis on Nesi's Notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/07/legal-context-can-woonsocket-successfully-sue-the-state-for-additional-aid.html"&gt;Second&lt;/a&gt;, I want to discuss the legal context of school funding in Rhode Island. This is especially interesting since Pawtucket and Woonsocket are both currently suing the state for additional funds for
the second time. I am going to review what happened the first time these communities brought their fight for education aid to the courthouse and explain why I believe this strategy will fail once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/07/using-the-common-core-data-on-nces.html"&gt;Third&lt;/a&gt;, I want to provide instructions on precisely how I retrieved the data and created the graphs in that post. I am a firm believer in "reproducible research", so I want to be entirely transparent on my data
sources and methods. I also think that too few people are acquainted with the Common Core Data provided by the National Center for Education Statistics that I relied on exclusively for my guest blog. Hopefully these instructions will help more concerned citizens and journalists in Rhode Island use data to back up assertions about local education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please reserve your comments on my original posts for Nesi's Notes. I have disabled comments on this post, because I would like to keep the comments on the original analysis contained in one place. Feel free to
comment on each of the follow up posts.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="education"></category><category term="nesi's notes"></category><category term="rhode island"></category><category term="ri"></category><category term="tax policy"></category><category term="woonsocket"></category></entry><entry><title>Legal Context: Can Woonsocket Successfully Sue the State for Additional Aid?</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/07/legal-context-can-woonsocket-successfully-sue-the-state-for-additional-aid.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-07-12T09:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-07-12:2012/07/legal-context-can-woonsocket-successfully-sue-the-state-for-additional-aid.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My last post ended with an important question, "Who is responsible for ensuring students are receiving a certain minimum quality education?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my attempt at answering that question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the state have a legal obligation to fiscally ensure that Woonsocket students are receiving an equitable, adequate, and meaningful education? &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.oyez.org/cases/1970-1979/1972/1972_71_1332"&gt;San Antonio v. Rodriquez&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, a landmark Supreme Court case decided in 1973 determined that there was no fundamental right to education guaranteed by the U.S. Constitution. Since that decision, advocates for fairer education funding have focused their efforts in state courts arguing over provisions in state constitutions that include some rights to education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Rhode Island, the &lt;a href="http://www.educationjustice.org/states/rhodeisland.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;City of Pawtucket v. Sundlun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 1995 tested &lt;a href="http://www.rilin.state.ri.us/RiConstitution/C12.html"&gt;Article XII&lt;/a&gt; of the state constitution which stated "it shall be the duty of the general assembly to promote public schools...". In this case, East Greenwich, Pawtucket, and Woonsocket sued the state claiming that the duty to promote public schools amounted to a guarantee of equitable, adequate education funding from the state, a burden not met by the current General Assembly education aid distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a legal expert, but I find the &lt;a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=2372498001429988039&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;as_sdt=2,40&amp;amp;as_vis=1"&gt;conclusions of the Supreme Court&lt;/a&gt; abundantly clear. In &lt;em&gt;Pawtucket&lt;/em&gt;, the court decides to overturn a Superior Court decision which had earlier ruled that the state constitution guaranteed each child, "receive an equal, adequate, and meaningful education." &lt;em&gt;Pawtucket&lt;/em&gt; finds that the General Assembly's responsibility to "promote" as "&lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; sees fit" (emphasis added in the original decision) is quite narrow; the General Assembly clearly has the power to determine how to "promote" education, it has historically used that power in a way that relied on local appropriations to education, and the courts do not even have a judicable standard&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;to determine the General Assembly has failed to "promote" education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current lawsuit asserts two things have dramatically changed since &lt;em&gt;Pawtucket&lt;/em&gt; that justify a second look and new ruling&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. First, one portion of the state constitution has recently been changed that was used in the prior ruling. The Supreme Court's decision stated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, in no measure did the 1986 Constitution alter the plenary and exclusive powers of the General Assembly. In fact, the 1986 Constitution provided that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The general assembly shall continue to exercise the powers it has heretofore exercised, unless prohibited in this Constitution." Art. 6, sec. 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the judge stated that this section of the state constitution meant that the legislature was retaining the right to exercise its powers as it had historically. In the case of education, this means "the power to promote public education through a statutory funding scheme and through reliance on local property taxation," in accordance with the findings in the decision. However, Article 6, section 10 of the state constitution has subsequently been repealed. It is worth repeating what I said previously, &lt;strong&gt;I am not a legal expert&lt;/strong&gt;. However, I find the argument to overturn &lt;em&gt;Pawtucket&lt;/em&gt; on the basis that the General Assembly is no longer expressly continuing to exercise their power as previously to be weak. My understanding of the &lt;em&gt;Pawtucket&lt;/em&gt; ruling is that the court had only strengthened importance of historical context in making this decision by leaning on this constitutional provision. The importance of historical context still remains, even without this provision. In the &lt;em&gt;Pawtucket&lt;/em&gt; decision, the "exercise of powers it has heretofore exercised" is interpreted to mean that unchanged constitutional language reflects unchanged powers. By maintaining the same language in 1986, despite amendments offered that would have more explicitly established a right to education, the General Assembly was, in effect, affirming its intent to continue to &lt;em&gt;promote&lt;/em&gt; education as it had in the past. The plaintiffs in the current case, presumably, will argue that without Article 6, section 10, the General Assembly is allowing the courts to reinterpret even the same language to imply a different set of rights and responsibilities than it has historically. I have to ask, if the General Assembly's intent was to signal that Article XII should now be interpreted as establishing a right to education, why wouldn't they have adopted new, clearer language as was proposed in 1986? Having full awareness of the decision in &lt;em&gt;Pawtucket&lt;/em&gt;, it is hard to see that the General Assembly would signal a change in its power and responsibility to promote education through a repeal of Article 6, section 10. I would assert this change simply shifts some of the burden to the finding that the General Assembly &lt;em&gt;sees fit&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;em&gt;promot[ion]&lt;/em&gt; of some judicable standard right to education that is the state's fiscal responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the critical piece that the plaintiffs will not find. Nowhere has the General Assembly exercised its power to &lt;em&gt;promote &lt;/em&gt;in this way. In fact, one only has to look at how the General Assembly has acted to establish a judicable right to education to observe precisely how &lt;em&gt;it sees fit&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href="http://www.rilin.state.ri.us/statutes/title16/16-7/16-7-24.htm"&gt;Rhode Island General Law 16-7-24&lt;/a&gt;, titled "Minimum appropriation by a community for approved school expenses," is a provision that all school committees are quite familiar with. Here, the General Assembly do establish a judicable standard for education, set by the Board of Regents of Elementary and Secondary Education in regulations known as the "basic education program". But where &lt;em&gt;Pawtucket&lt;/em&gt; fails to establish a &lt;strong&gt;constitutional guarantee for state funding&lt;/strong&gt; in a particular amount for education, Rhode Island &lt;strong&gt;statute&lt;/strong&gt; is quite clear on a minimum standard for &lt;strong&gt;local&lt;/strong&gt; support. The law states that "Each community shall appropriate or otherwise make available... an amount, which together with state education and federal aid... shall be not less than the costs of the basic program... The Board of Regents for Elementary and Secondary Education shall adopt regulations for determining the basic education program..." In other words, Rhode Island statute squarely places the burden for meeting the Basic Education Program on cities and towns raising the required revenue. "A community that has a local appropriation insufficient to fund the basic education program … shall be required to increase its local appropriation…"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems pretty clear to me. While the plaintiffs in the current case will presumably argue that state regulations and laws &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; represent a judicable standard, they will be unable to find where the General Assembly, through action, has affirmed that it is the role of the state aid to meet this standard. Instead, the law directly states that &lt;strong&gt;local appropriations&lt;/strong&gt; are to be increased if the Basic Education Program cannot be met. I cannot imagine that the Supreme Court would exercise its power to assert that the General Assembly's inaction implies more about the purpose of &lt;em&gt;unchanged&lt;/em&gt; constitutional language than the General Assembly's actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, although the city is again suing the state for additional education aid, it is clear in the last 15 years that the state has substantially increased its support for Woonsocket Schools&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Furthermore, previous Rhode Island Supreme Court decisions and Rhode Island law clearly places the burden of adequate school funding squarely on the shoulders of cities and towns, not the General Assembly. In my view, the changes in education law and policy since &lt;em&gt;Pawtucket&lt;/em&gt; do not imply a change that would impact the court's ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is the second post of a three-part follow up on my &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/category/nesis-notes/"&gt;guest post&lt;/a&gt; for Nesi's Notes. Parts I and III can be found &lt;a href="http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/?p=224"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;meaning measurable and enforceable by court room activities&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: I have not read the complaint as I probably should have for this post. I ran out of time. However, I feel fairly certain from press coverage that I am correctly stating their main points&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See my post on Nesi's Notes&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="education"></category><category term="nesi's notes"></category><category term="Pawtucket v. Sundlun"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="rhode island"></category><category term="ri"></category><category term="rigl"></category><category term="woonsocket"></category></entry><entry><title>Limitations of the Nesi's Notes Analysis and Some Additional Questions</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/07/limitations-of-the-nesis-notes-analysis-and-some-additional-questions.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-07-12T09:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-07-12:2012/07/limitations-of-the-nesis-notes-analysis-and-some-additional-questions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are several questions that come to mind when looking over my analysis on &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/category/nesis-notes/"&gt;Nesi's Notes&lt;/a&gt;. The first thing I wondered was whether or not Woonsocket had raised local revenues by similar amounts to other communities but had chosen to spend this money on other municipal services. Ideally, I would use a chart that showed local education revenues compared to all other local revenues over the last 15 years by city in Rhode Island. Unfortunately, &lt;a href="http://www.muni-info.ri.gov/"&gt;Municipal Finance&lt;/a&gt; does not separate local, state, and federal revenue sources in the &lt;a href="http://www.muni-info.ri.gov/finances/municipal_budget_survey.php"&gt;Municipal Budget Survey&lt;/a&gt; so it is hard to know&lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; communities have funded different services. I am sure with a bit of finagling, I could come up with a fairly good guess as to whether or not Woonsocket has simply chosen to fund other municipal services with its taxes, but quite frankly it is not precise enough to make me feel like its worth the exercise of extracting data from PDF tables. I hope someone else will take up some form of this analysis, possibly by requesting the breakdowns from Municipal Finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another consideration is whether there is any truth to Woonsocket's claims that it simply does not have the ability to generate enough local revenue for their schools. I am skeptical on this claim. Three pieces of evidence suggest to me that this may not be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The magnitude of the shortfall between the rest of the state and Woonsocket over the last 15 years when it comes to local education revenue&lt;/strong&gt;. On its face, I don't find it credible that Woonsocket's tax base is so weak that it could not increase local revenues for schools even at the rate of inflation. Not increasing local revenue for schools seems to leave only two possibilities: 1) local revenues in general were not increased, meaning Woonsocket would have to argue that its taxation in FY95 was so high relative to everyone else that it took nearly 15 years for the rest of the state to catch up, hence no additional revenues; or 2) Woonsocket did raise local revenues, and chose to spend the money elsewhere. Had Woonsocket's local education aid risen 65-75% versus a state average of around 100%, I probably would not have even written my post on Nesi's Notes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/#!/candrewmorse"&gt;Andrew Morse&lt;/a&gt;'s analysis presented on &lt;a href="http://www.anchorrising.com/barnacles/013927.html"&gt;Anchor Rising&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Woonsocket appears to be on the low to typical end of revenues as a proportion of non-poverty income. It does not seem that they are anywhere near the "most" taxed city or town by this measure. I am not an expert on tax policy, but this measure seems fairly straightforward, fair, and informative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The mammoth proportions of Woonsocket's budget being spent on pensions (through debt service) and other post-employment benefits&lt;/strong&gt;. [A full 15% or so of Woonsocket's local revenues are being spent in these areas][]. This suggests to me misappropriation and poor planning has led to the erosion of local support for schools, not a lack of revenue generating capacity. If this truly is the case, then Woonsocket residents are really in trouble. Their leaders have managed to generate all of the high costs and high taxes experienced in Rhode Island without providing the quality of service that should be expected given those investments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I failed to offer any recommendation for remedy in the Nesi's Note post. How should Woonsocket schools become "whole" again? How can this possibly be accomplished in the context of a city on the brink of financial failure? Who has the legal responsibility to ensure that Woonsocket's children get the education they deserve? I have no answers on the first two points. However, in the next section of this post I hope answer the last question, which is also the subject of a law suit filed by Pawtucket and Woonsocket against the state of Rhode Island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who is responsible for ensuring students are receiving a certain minimum quality education?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is the first of a three-part follow up on my &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/category/nesis-notes/"&gt;guest post&lt;/a&gt; for Nesi's Notes. Parts II and III can be found
&lt;a href="http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/?p=224"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[fourth lowest revenues from residential taxes as a proportion of
community wealth]: http://www.anchorrising.com/barnacles/014501.html
[A full 15% or so of Woonsocket's local revenues are being spent in
these areas]: http://blogs.reuters.com/muniland/2012/06/20/conservative-ideologues-arent-bankrupting-rhode-island/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew has been writing quite a bit about Woonsocket. For his most recent post, Andrew demonstrates Woonsocket has the [fourth lowest revenues from residential taxes as a proportion of community wealth][]. A few things I'd like to point out on that post. First, I think Andrew was right to adjust for poverty in previous posts in a way he was unable to due to the structure of the new data. I support progressive taxation, so I don't believe that it is fair to say that we should expect the same percentage of income tax from poorer communities that we do from wealthier ones. I also think that commercial taxes are very important revenue sources. I don't think they should be universally dismissed when used as a substitute from residential revenues. There are times where marginally the greatest benefit can be had by lowering residents' taxes. However, I do think that commercial tax should not be used as a substitute when there isn't enough revenue in the pie. In Woonsocket's case, it seems pretty clear they needed both the residential and commercial taxes to have sufficient revenues. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="education"></category><category term="nesi's notes"></category><category term="poverty"></category><category term="rhode island"></category><category term="ri"></category><category term="tax policy"></category><category term="woonsocket"></category></entry><entry><title>Update on Social Promotion</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/07/update-on-social-promotion.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-07-10T09:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-07-10:2012/07/update-on-social-promotion.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href="http://www.startinganedschool.org/2012/07/09/letter-from-an-8th-grader/"&gt;poignant post&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.startinganedschool.org/author/mike/"&gt;Michael Goldstein&lt;/a&gt; ends with a few policy thoughts that largely support my &lt;a href="http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/2012/02/15/social-promotion-tutoring-and-funding/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goldstein's second point is worth highlighting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, in a small school, large-scale research isn’t the key
determinant anyway. The team’s implementation is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the same day that &lt;a href="http://shankerblog.org"&gt;Shanker Blog&lt;/a&gt; is assuring us that &lt;a href="http://shankerblog.org/?p=6180"&gt;rigorous social science is worth it&lt;/a&gt;, Goldstein delivers researchers a healthy dose of humility. Rigorous research is all about doing the best we can to remove all the confounding explanatory factors that have an impact on our observed outcomes to isolate an intervention. But even in the most rigorous studies social scientists are often measuring the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Average_treatment_effect"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;verage &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;reatment &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;ffect&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How rarely do we truly encounter a completely average situation? The real impact in any particular school or organization can be dramatically different in magnitude and even direction because of all the pesky observed and &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omitted-variable_bias"&gt;unobserved&lt;/a&gt; confounding factors that researchers work so hard to be able to &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Validity_(statistics)"&gt;ignore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my advice? If you are down on the ground keep close to the research but keep closer to your intuition, provided you are ready, willing, and able to monitor, evaluate, and adjust.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="education"></category><category term="education policy"></category><category term="education reform"></category><category term="intervention"></category><category term="MATCH"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="social promotion"></category><category term="Starting an Ed School"></category></entry><entry><title>Work Place Liberty in the Context of Education</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/07/work-place-liberty-in-the-context-of-education.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-07-09T09:40:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-07-09:2012/07/work-place-liberty-in-the-context-of-education.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How can we tell if principal directives are fair to teachers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been a great conversation circling some blogs I read over the last week about liberty in the work place.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Issues of fairness in the work place are a constant in today's education conversation. Whether some view it as a form of metaphoric violence on teachers and their profession, while others see a concerted effort to change rigid, bureaucratic systems that prevent effective change&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, at the heart of education reform &lt;em&gt;du jour&lt;/em&gt; are changes to workplace freedom. Improving human capital systems has meant dismantling questionable licensing requirements&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, dramatic changes in &lt;a href="http://www.ride.ri.gov/EducatorQuality/EducatorEvaluation/Default.aspx"&gt;teacher&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://dcps.dc.gov/DCPS/In+the+Classroom/Ensuring+Teacher+Success/IMPACT+(Performance+Assessment)/An+Overview+of+IMPACT"&gt;evaluation&lt;/a&gt;, and other dramatic changes to who gets &lt;a href="http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/2012/may/11/reviews-to-favor-effective-teachers/?print=1"&gt;hired&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LIFO_(education)"&gt;fired&lt;/a&gt;. Using extended learning time, either through additional instructional days and/or longer school days, to increase student achievement is often considered too costly, because teachers demand more pay for more work. Additional professional development days are similarly costly; teachers are loath to give up additional days in the summer or during school vacations without receiving additional pay. I could go on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these reforms seek to radically change terms and benefits in teacher contracts and state law that represent a string of hard-fought (and won) battles that teachers and their unions pursued for years. The political left, and more specifically the progressive movement, has generally picked up on these attempts as anti-union, anti-collective bargaining, anti-democratic, anti-teacher, and anti-education. There are even a host of conspiracy theories decrying the "corporate reformers" who are coming into the education realm to break down good, public, democratic systems that are good for Democrats, largely to hurt poor kids and make profits&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, most of this argument is about what individuals ideologies have led them to believe about employee rights and employer rights. I find it increasingly frustrating that these conversations do not address the deeper philosophical differences. This is why I have really enjoyed observing the current conversation between &lt;a href="http://crookedtimber.org/"&gt;Crooked Timber&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://bleedingheartlibertarians.com/"&gt;Bleeding Heart Libertarians&lt;/a&gt;, and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspects of the BRG argument&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;is that worker contracts are unique because many of the terms of employment are ambiguous. Employers should only be permitted to demand that employees partake in activities to which they have consented. The contract is supposedly a signal of this consent, however, because the terms are so often ambiguous, disputes over whether or not it covers an activity are practically a guarantee. So how should these disputes be settled and by whom? BRG would argue that there should be strong worker freedom to make sure that their consent is truly given. They consider the relationship between employer and employee to be naturally coercive, at least in part because they assume the right to end employment has very asymmetric benefits since employees have, presumably, much more to lose than employers when the contract ends. BRG assumes that freedom is best served through a democratic workplace with very powerful employees who have few, if any of their rights restricted in the workplace. On the other hand, BHLers believe that it is possible to consent to restrict ones rights within a contractual relationship, they do not tend to accept that the right to exit affords highly asymmetric freedoms&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and they feel that freedom is maximized by abstaining from limiting private contracts while maximizing the rights to freely enter and exit contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is macroeconomist Miles Kimball, a recent entrant into the &lt;a href="http://blog.supplysideliberal.com/"&gt;blogosphere&lt;/a&gt;, whose &lt;a href="http://blog.supplysideliberal.com/post/26531357710/jobs"&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt; I felt could most directly be applied to education. If I were to summarize his post, it would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are significant pressures against to eliminating freedoms of
    your workers that end up making them worse at their jobs or lead to
    attracting bad talent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although these pressures exist for "The Firm", it is true that
    "underbosses" with significant power can act in ways that maximize
    their personal gain instead of what's good for "The Firm" and the
    pressures are less strong against eliminating freedoms for them than
    the organization as a whole.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nevertheless, they should have the rights to limit/remove freedoms,
    and these limitations should be based on whether they are relevant
    to achieving the organizations pre-stated mission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ultimately, the right outside force to judge whether this was a
    proper imposition to make on employees should be people who have
    successfully navigated the same challenges as The Firm but have no
    direct interest in The Firms current activities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these four points, if they are accepted as true, has some interesting applications to education. My translation for education colleagues would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Districts and states have little reason to make lives shitty for
    teachers. &lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:7" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some principals, department heads, and others may have the ability to act in ways that are less than proper. &lt;sup id="fnref:8"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:8" rel="footnote"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actions that restrict teacher rights should be judged on whether they help the school achieve the district or school's pre-stated mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disputes between teachers and their bosses, should not be adjudicated by a typical jury or judge. Instead, the actions of the principal should be judged by other principals who have been successful, preferably with some distance from the actual organization (i.e. not principals who might compete for the offending principals job or may want to hire or be stuck with that teacher based on the proceedings).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that points 1 and 2 are fairly obvious. Points 3 and 4, however, are far more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kimball is attempting to split the difference a fascinating way. I believe he would accept that employment contracts are, by necessity, "ambiguous" in the way that BRG defines that term. His argument is, therefore, that the mission and purpose of the organization &lt;strong&gt;should not&lt;/strong&gt;be ambiguous. So long as the organization's mission is clear, an employment contract becomes consent to do whatever has a rational basis for furthering those goals. In this way, there is an ethical standard by which we can judge new situations that could never have been anticipated directly at the contracting stage. For example, it may be perfectly reasonable for a principal to require a teacher to spend lunch in the student cafeteria so long as their is a rational basis for believing this would further the mission of the school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In highly unionized workplaces, work rules are so specific that they remove a substantial portion of the ambiguity in contracting. This is generally seen by the left, union members, and other BRG-like thinkers as a huge victory. It implies full consent to the terms of employment and substantial restriction of an employer's ability to abuse their position and abridge the freedoms of their employees in unethical ways. Schools are generally like this. Practically everything is spelled out about a teacher's position, often to the minute. How long they get to eat lunch, how much unstructured time they get during the day, how long they have to spend time working with other teachers, how long they are allowed to be placed in front of kids, how many kids can be placed in front of a teacher at any given time, these conditions and more are detailed in teacher contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, when I ask a union supporter why they think unions are good, they almost always point out "abuses" of employers that occurred often before the union wrestled power from the grips of the few and the privileged back to the laborers. I have to wonder how much of their support comes from a lack of common, clear definition of unethical abridgments of freedom in the workplace. The solution to this ambiguity is requiring that all actions be consented to through negotiation and contracting, which also determines that dispute resolution is a matter of contract law. I have to wonder if both workers and their employers would be better off if there was a universal ethical standard like Kimball proposes. This way consent can be given while allowing more ambiguity in the contract itself. Right now employers fight for this ambiguity depending solely on appeals to trust and cooperation, two things that are rarely earned before working with someone as would be required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't say that I understand labor dispute resolution well enough to comment on the differences between Kimball's fourth suggestion and current practice. However, it is pretty clear to me that enforcement through contract law is costly and inefficient, regardless whether it is effective in adjudicating disputes in an ethical matter. Labor relations boards, as far as I can tell, seem to be a political tool swaying between dramatically increasing worker power, especially when members are current or former full-time employees and members of a union, and increasing employer power when more corporate representation is assured. If only I believed it were possible to have an apolitical, disinterested board, with sector-specific expertise, determine whether there is a "rational basis" for employer actions that Kimball envisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am left with more questions than answers, but, for me, there is a rich appeal to utilizing the mission of an organization to determine whether the actions of both it and its employees are just.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://crookedtimber.org/2012/07/01/let-it-bleed-libertarianism-and-the-workplace/"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the (socialist?) critique of libertarians and right to work that sparked the discussion. Then &lt;a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2012/07/libertarianism-and-the-workplace.html"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; economists &lt;a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2012/07/libertarianism-and-the-workplace-ii.html"&gt;jumped&lt;/a&gt; in. The &lt;a href="http://bleedingheartlibertarians.com/2012/07/freedom-and-work/"&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; from Bleeding Heart Libertarians, meanwhile, &lt;a href="http://bleedingheartlibertarians.com/2012/07/libertarianism-the-workplace-and-the-reconciling-power-of-the-social-moral-order/"&gt;continues&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://bleedingheartlibertarians.com/2012/07/denmark-vs-france/"&gt;to&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://bleedingheartlibertarians.com/2012/07/why-are-employers-so-mean/"&gt;pour&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://bleedingheartlibertarians.com/2012/07/my-bottom-line-on-worker-freedom/"&gt;in&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://bleedingheartlibertarians.com/2012/07/cruelty-and-power/"&gt;rapidly&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lean toward the latter, even if I disagree sometimes both with the means and ends of the current reform movement.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am skeptical about &lt;a href="http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2012/05/occupational-licensing-and-low-income.html"&gt;licensing in general&lt;/a&gt;. I've seen substantially more &lt;a href="http://www0.gsb.columbia.edu/faculty/jrockoff/certification-final.pdf"&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; to support experience than licensing requirements in education and/or additional education. Various &lt;a href="http://tntp.org/"&gt;alternative&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.teachforamerica.org/"&gt;teacher&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.bostonteacherresidency.org/"&gt;pathways&lt;/a&gt; now exist. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas I find some of the "anti-s" in the previous sentence worthy of discussion, I find the massive, corporate, right-wing conspiracy stuff to be 98% bullocks. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BRG= Bertram, Robin, and Gourevitch, authors of the Crooked Timber post. This acronym has been used in contrast with BHL, Bleeding Heart Libertarians, during this debate &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or perhaps, if they do they feel that this would not be the case in a world that more generally matched BHLs principles &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I assume that the proper size unit for "The Firm" is above the school. I think this generally holds because district boards and state policy makers tend to be more directly accountable to citizens than schools. The relationship here is much more like shareholders and/or customers to business than the citizen to school relationship. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, the school-level administration represents the "underbosses". Given that much of the debate over teacher evaluation and rules on hiring and firing stem from debates about both principal quality and principal power, I think this is the right assignment. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:8" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="bleeding heart libertarians"></category><category term="economics"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="libertarianism"></category><category term="liberty"></category><category term="political philosophy"></category><category term="public-sector unions"></category><category term="teacher evaluation"></category><category term="union"></category></entry><entry><title>Value-Added on Core Knowledge Blog-- some thoughts on Chetty, Friedman, and Rockoff</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/01/value-added-on-core-knowledge-blog-some-thoughts-on-chetty-friedman-and-rockoff.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-13T00:08:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-01-13:2012/01/value-added-on-core-knowledge-blog-some-thoughts-on-chetty-friedman-and-rockoff.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jessica Lahey wrote an &lt;a href="http://blog.coreknowledge.org/2012/01/12/what-is-the-value-in-a-high-value-added-teacher/"&gt;interesting post&lt;/a&gt; over on &lt;a href="http://blog.coreknowledge.org/"&gt;Core Knowledge Blog&lt;/a&gt; that I decided to comment on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I read back my comment, I realized it would be worth copying over here as it's own blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting part of the &lt;a href="http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/chetty"&gt;Chetty&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.hks.harvard.edu/fs/jfriedm/"&gt;Friedman&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www0.gsb.columbia.edu/faculty/jrockoff/"&gt;Rockoff&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://nber.org/papers/w17699"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; is precisely the most banal- teachers who improve heir students learning as measured by increased achievement on tandardized tests also improve other more distant and relevant factors n children’s lives &lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems obvious to anyone who isn’t vehemently anti-testing. For a large group of the anti-testing regime, there is considerable skepticism that the standardized testing intruments being used by states is a valid instrument for the “real” purposes of education. In fact, the line of thinking in this post is a close relative to this critique. Essentially, what is mathematically reliable is not necessarily valid for drawing conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CFR in a massive study essentially: 1) Added to a large research base that suggests that teachers can in fact have an impact on standardized test scores; 2) Demonstrate that the impact on standardized test scores are associated with broader, more distant, and, arguably, more important education outcomes; 3) These impacts are persistent throughout the lifetime of students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it does NOT make a great case for teacher dismissal based solely on VAM, like the authors are essentially claiming in popular coverage, it does continue to strengthen the case that standardized tests are relevant, reliable, and meaningful indicators of a successful education system. The impacts on social outcomes (teen pregnancy) and economic outcomes (later earnings) show a broad range of important outcomes we expect from schools are strongly associated with VAMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good measure does not have to perfectly describe the intracacies of reality, it just has to give a rough, reasonable, and valid facsimile. CFR is just part of a growing tradition that shows there’s a good case for VAMs to be a part of that image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, I think that &lt;a href="http://schoolfinance101.wordpress.com/2012/01/07/fire-first-ask-questions-later-comments-on-recent-teacher-effectiveness-studies/"&gt;Baker&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://shankerblog.org/?p=4708"&gt;Di Carlo&lt;/a&gt;, nd &lt;a href="http://shermandorn.com/wordpress/?p=4390"&gt;Dorn&lt;/a&gt; are all probably right that the tests for biasness in VAMs or teachers are the most interesting part, but that's purely from a geeky researcher perspective. I doubt that'll have as much impact as ther portions of the paper, and probably rightfully so&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Core Knowledge Blog"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="standardized tests"></category><category term="teacher evaluation"></category><category term="value-added measures"></category><category term="VAM"></category></entry><entry><title>House wants unemployed to earn GEDs against all economic sense</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2011/12/house-wants-unemployed-to-earn-geds-against-all-economic-sense.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-12-14T17:58:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2011-12-14:2011/12/house-wants-unemployed-to-earn-geds-against-all-economic-sense.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here is a doozy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the purpose of the GED? Is it a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signalling_(economics)"&gt;market signal&lt;/a&gt;, indicating your employability to hiring agents or does it follow a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_capital"&gt;human capital&lt;/a&gt; path wherein earning a GED is actually a process that increases your skill set?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The House wants all unemployed workers without a high school diploma &lt;a href="http://blogs.edweek.org/edweek/campaign-k-12/2011/12/bill_would_require_ged_to_tap.html"&gt;to earn their GED&lt;/a&gt;. Their explanation is assuming that the GED works purely through human capital theory, e.g. currently unemployed workers who don't have a high school diploma will earn more skills that make them increasingly employable by enrolling in and earning their GED. Is there any evidence for this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at what the &lt;a href="http://www.brown.edu/Departments/Education/resources/what_do_we_know.pdf"&gt;research says&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:research"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:research" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, we learn that the GED is only effective at boosting earnings of lower skilled recipients. Tyler suggests that this may indicate that the GED is acting as a labor market signal, demonstrating to future employers that they have the work ethic and extra motivation low-skilled high school drop-outs are believed to lack and are worth hiring. This is supported by the fact that not only are low skilled GED earners the only ones who see greater earnings and employability as a result of earning a GED but also by the fact that there is a lag to the "GED impact". One possible mechanism for this lag indicates that the GED is a signal for unobserved characteristics that suggest an employee is ready to learn and earn those additional skills they do not current possess, and therefore, low-skilled workers who earn a GED are more likely to be placed in a position where they will have the opportunity to increase their human capital and future earnings. Since high skilled employees don't seem to gain any benefit from a GED, that suggests that their existing skill set already sufficiently operates as a signal of employability such that there is no need for an additional signal of initial readiness for hiring. Even if this were the case, if the GED was truly ruled by a human capital model, we would expect high skilled GED recipients to have become increasingly skilled through the GED process and, therefore, they should also benefit from increased earnings due to receiving a GED.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does this all mean? Let's remember that the unemployment benefits being offered only exist for 99 weeks now (and would be lowered to 59 weeks in the House proposal). This means that all the unemployed we're worried about were in fact employed within the last year and seven weeks. Do we believe that those who were employed as recently as one year ago, already deep into the economic downturn, who do not have a high school diploma fall into the low or high skilled group? It seems obvious to me that if you were employable 59 weeks ago you would almost certainly be in the upper half (if not higher) of the skills distribution among those who don't have high school diplomas. So the result of the GED policy is likely going to lead to no benefit for these workers and will probably even decrease their earnings since they will have some costs associated with earning the GED-- be it the fee for a course, the fee to take the test, the opportunity costs associated with spending time studying and working toward a credential that has no benefit, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worse, by dramatically changing the contexts where folks earn a GED, we're likely to completely change what signal the GED will send future employers. In essence, the impact is unpredictable, but it's hard to see a path whereby earning a GED increases in value as a result of policies that make certain that GEDs will be earned more broadly and under duress and not  by voluntary action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So forget about all the other stuff you read on the GED requirement. We don't have to worry about fairness, discrimination, or just plain shitting on people when they're in some of the most dire straits they're likely to see by adding even more to their burdens. The GED-only policy on unemployment benefits is simply unlikely to do anything other than transfer resources from the unemployed to the &lt;a href="http://www.acenet.edu/AM/Template.cfm?Section=Home"&gt;American Council on Education&lt;/a&gt; and companies that have GED &lt;a href="http://www.kaptest.com/ged"&gt;prep&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.randomhouse.com/princetonreview/college/ged/"&gt;classes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:research"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Tyler was a former professor of mine. If Brown had a PhD programming in education, I would go back in a heartbeat to work under him.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:research" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="brown university"></category><category term="economics"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="GED"></category><category term="human capital"></category><category term="john tyler"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="signaling"></category><category term="unemployment"></category></entry><entry><title>Diane Ravitch, rebuttals.</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2011/12/diane-ravitch-rebuttals.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-12-12T15:23:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2011-12-12:2011/12/diane-ravitch-rebuttals.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I wrote a &lt;a href="http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/2011/11/28/is-diane-ravitch-a-reliable-historian/"&gt;harsh post&lt;/a&gt; after reading a &lt;a href="http://www.tnr.com/print/article/politics/magazine/97765/diane-ravitch-education-reform"&gt;harsh article&lt;/a&gt; by Kevin Carey in &lt;a href="http://www.tnr.com/"&gt;The New Republic&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href="http://www.dianeravitch.com/"&gt;Diane Ravitch&lt;/a&gt;. I still standby what I said. Namely, I'm very cautious about trusting Ravitch as a reliable narrator of history because I'm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unfamiliar with good historiography/methodology so it's hard for me to judge the quality of her work simply from the product itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unaware of a rich discourse around education history in NYC and 20th century America in general that wrestles with, or even corroborates, Ravitch's account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;certain that Ravitch's more recent writings often mischaracterizes the power and meaning behind quantitative research and exhibits selection bias to fit a particular narrative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;generally distrustful of public academics, particularly when their writing is mainly outside of their primary discipline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, there have been several well-written critiques of Carey's piece and I thought it's only fair that I link to them to present a more complete picture of what many folks, some who agree and some who disagree with Ravitch's current ideology, think of Ravitch's work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.edexcellence.net/about-us/people/michael-j-petrilli.html"&gt;Mike Petrilli&lt;/a&gt; is certainly no fan of Ravitch's rebirth as the anti-choice, anti-accountability voice &lt;em&gt;du jour&lt;/em&gt;. But &lt;a href="http://www.educationgadfly.net/flypaper/2011/11/what-kevin-carey-didnt-say-about-diane-ravitch-but-should-have/"&gt;his piece&lt;/a&gt; in Flypaper in response to Carey is quite clear: the idea that Ravitch's personal life  had an impact on her criticism of then NYC Schools
Chancellor &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joel_Klein"&gt;Joel Klein&lt;/a&gt; is unfair and wrong. As someone who worked directly with Ravitch and who had, independently, overseen the awarding of a grant to &lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/mary-butz"&gt;Mary Butz&lt;/a&gt;'s leadership program, Petrilli sees a different line of thought. Ravitch, in his view, simply correctly pointed to the flaw in Klein's "clear the field" approach that tended to cut down successful or promising programs alongside the dead weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.danagoldstein.net/dana_goldstein/about-dana.html"&gt;Dana Goldstein&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="http://www.danagoldstein.net/dana_goldstein/2011/11/thoughts-on-kevin-careys-profile-of-diane-ravitch-history-and-ideology.html"&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; suggests that Kevin Carey ignored the context in which Ravitch wrote. Goldstein suggests that Ravitch had to fight against a sexist academy in a discipline that increasingly had taken on a polemicists tone, as a liberal who did not quite fit the mold
of her times. These factors combined to generate the type of histories and writing that Ravitch would produce and are critical in understanding, without undermining, her work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href="http://www.dianasenechal.com/bio.html"&gt;Diane Senechal&lt;/a&gt; writes in The New Republic &lt;a href="http://www.tnr.com/article/politics/98379/diane-ravitch-school-reform?page=0,0"&gt;today&lt;/a&gt; that Ravitch's history is a far more balanced critique than Carey would have you believe, very well documented, and self-consistent. She does concede that Ravitch writes with a fiery, decidedly non-academic tone that's
intended as a public intellectual. But here, Senechal views this as a strength, "arous[ing] general interest in matters that might otherwise seem out of reach or obscure." Ultimately, Senechal's main point is that Ravitch's work is of very high quality and thorough and that her tone should not overshadow the accomplishment of her scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="dana goldstein"></category><category term="diane ravitch"></category><category term="edreform"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="education policy"></category><category term="education reform"></category><category term="history"></category><category term="kevin carey"></category><category term="mike petrilli"></category><category term="tnr"></category></entry><entry><title>Contracting Technology in Education</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2011/11/contracting-technology-in-education.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-11-29T22:40:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2011-11-29:2011/11/contracting-technology-in-education.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am glad that &lt;a href="http://gothamschools.org/author/philissa-cramer/"&gt;Philissa Cramer&lt;/a&gt; is reporting on some of the deeper details of the Special Education Student Information System &lt;sup id="fnref:coverage"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:coverage" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; implementation at the &lt;a href="http://schools.nyc.gov/default.htm"&gt;New York City Department&lt;/a&gt; of Education &lt;a href="http://gothamschools.org/2011/11/29/report-links-sesis-struggles-and-does-contractinpractices/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Many people don't really understand the ins and outs of government contracting. Folks really think NASA designs and builds the lunar module, for example, instead of realizing that they issued an RFP and contracting with &lt;a href="http://www.northropgrumman.com/"&gt;Northrop Grumman&lt;/a&gt; to do that work for them. Similarly, in education, especially around complex technology projects, most districts and states purchase products or services through a bid product rather than develop solutions in house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I am a bit disappointed in the angle that &lt;a href="http://www.citylimits.org"&gt;City Limits&lt;/a&gt;, (Ms. Cramer's &lt;a href="http://www.theinvestigativefund.org/investigations/politicsandgovernment/1581/beyond_citytime?page=1"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;) took in their reporting. There are real problems with government contracting, but they really mischaracterize the story around SESIS in an attempt to simplify the issue for casual readers.
City Limits acts as though it is surprising, or even deplorable, that an RFP was awarded to a company with a largely existing product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They point to the fact that Maximus, the vendor for the SESIS contract, was modifying an existing product to meet the requirements outlined in NYC DOE's RFP as though this was clearly bad. City Limits uses words like "revealed" and "simply" to describe what Maximus was offering. This just ignores the reality of government contracting and shows disregard for risk mitigation. Almost all government agencies handsomely reward companies that can point to successes in developing and implementing solutions that can meet many of the requirements outlined in the issued RFP. The government wants to hire people it believes can do the job and do it well and often one of the best ways to make that determination is to see that someone has done it before. In almost all cases, this means selecting a vendor who has an existing product or process for meeting many of the requirements in the RFP that will be expanded upon or modified. But government purchasers don't just want experienced partners, they also want to leverage efficiencies by not paying for duplication. One of the major reasons for purchasing an existing product or contracting with a vendor is that school systems actually aren't that different from one another and the basic functionality and organizational structures required in an IT solution are shared across schools, districts, and states. Why pay substantially to build the same basic software infrastructure that already exists elsewhere? It's a waste of money most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;City Limits then goes on to criticize the massive increases that can occur due to change orders. This is a serious problem with government contracting, but they fail to really explore why. A change order occurs when the client wants new or additional functionality that was not included in the initial contract. Their frequency and expense are not an example of why government agencies should not contract with outside vendors, rather, they demonstrate just how poorly bureaucracies are at managing large-scale complex projects. Change orders happen due to several failures, and almost all are the government agencies' fault. In no particular order, the government agency:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;failed to do proper discovery before issuing the RFP and, therefore, missed major functional requirements that are not identified until more intensive discovery occurs during development or initial implementation;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;agreed to a contract that was far too specific and did not allow for the reality that requirements do evolve over time (though often not in ways which substantially change the nature or quantity of work);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;agreed to a contract that was far too vague such that the vendor can claim to have delivered a product or service when they did not meet already identified functional requirements for the system;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;did not take into account the preparation and costs required to sustain the product beyond the life of the initial engagement with the vendor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the main things that lead to change orders. If the government agency is doing a top-notch job, they can all be avoided and the only occasion for a change order should be large external shocks that dramatically alter the functional requirements, intentional decisions to move away from the initial functional requirements that weighed the costs of altering the vendor contract, and a desire to extend and expand a relationship because of the success of the initial implementation resulting in a substantially more advanced or mature product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is really hard to manage vendor contracts right. It requires actually knowing what you want to buy before an RFP is issued (or recognizing what is and is not known and correctly assessing the scope of the impact future decisions on unknowns will have on the work). It requires a really good team of lawyers to fight outside forces that literally make their profits on carefully abdicating as much responsibility as possible at the contracting phase. It requires selecting good partners that are adequately willing and prepared to evolve and work with the agency as their needs and knowledge grow and mature. It requires an honest assessment of future resources that will be available to assure sustainability of large investments. And perhaps most difficult of all, it requires strong project management infrastructure throughout the entire agency to ensure alignment and consistency across multiple products produced internally and by multiple external partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benefits of outsourcing products can be huge and are worth leveraging. Vendor contracts are difficult to manage, and bureaucracies are not always well-suited to managing these projects, but all government agencies struggle with getting this right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One last parting thought...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my view, the most challenging aspect of getting vendor contracting right for government agencies is spending ample upfront time, even before issuing an RFP, articulating the functional needs that a solution must meet in detail. I feel that often public sector employees are so
intimidated by the arduous process around issuing and awarding an RFP that they rush to get an RFP out there and worry about the details during contracting and product initiation. Whenever possible, resist this temptation at all costs. Whether custom designed internally or
provided by an external vendor, satisfaction is dependent upon clarity of the desired outcomes. This is particularly true with technology projects. Vendors will always produce &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;, but whether the solution is any good is almost entirely up to good requirements gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:coverage"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For pretty good coverage check out all of Gotham School's posts &lt;a href="http://gothamschools.org/tag/sesis/"&gt;http://gothamschools.org/tag/sesis/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:coverage" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="bureaucracy"></category><category term="business analysis"></category><category term="City LImits"></category><category term="Gotham Schools"></category><category term="government"></category><category term="government contracting"></category><category term="information technology"></category><category term="NYC DOE"></category><category term="Philissa Cramer"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="public goods"></category><category term="RFP"></category><category term="SESIS"></category><category term="vendor relationships"></category></entry><entry><title>Is Diane Ravitch a reliable historian?</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2011/11/is-diane-ravitch-a-reliable-historian.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-11-28T10:33:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2011-11-28:2011/11/is-diane-ravitch-a-reliable-historian.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATE: You should also read &lt;a href="http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/2011/12/12/diane-ravitch-rebuttals/"&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; on jasonpbecker for some very strong and interesting rebuttals to Carey's article that I commented on below.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do read &lt;a href="http://www.tnr.com/print/article/politics/magazine/97765/diane-ravitch-education-reform"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; on Diane Ravitch. I personally have two major criticisms of Ravitch, both of which Carey exposes eloquently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I believe that she leverages her respect and expertise as an historian and professor to present herself as an experts in areas of academic research and policy where she has little expertise. This is very common with public intellectuals, and I think it's deceiving and deplorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I am unsure about whether she is a reliable narrator of history because my impression is that she's the "best in the game" at least in part because so few are playing. I don't personally have the skill to judge her histories and given her blatant academic dishonesty in so many other areas where I have some ability to judge quality, I find it hard to view her as an honest operator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is somewhat new in Carey's take on Ravitch, and what I think most here on Plus will find interesting, are two revelations. First, one I was somewhat acquainted with, it seems possible that some of Ravitch's shift to rhetorical vitriol against someone who seemed a natural ally (Joel Klein) may be partially attributable to a personal dispute involving Ravitch's "partner" (this and other articles seem to be intentionally ambiguous about the nature of this relationship). Second, and most interesting to me, it appears that Ravitch doesn't have the typical academic acumen of an acclaimed scholar in her field. In fact, it appears that Ravitch has produced almost exclusively popular history throughout her career. This detail in particular plays into some of my very concerns about the reliability of her historical narratives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a side note, I think if I could be one person in education policy today it'd be Kevin Carey. He's smart as hell and an excellent writer, even if I disagree with him on higher education issues.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="carey"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="ravitch"></category></entry></feed>