<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>jasonpbecker</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/feeds/education.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.jsonbecker.com/</id><updated>2012-11-02T11:59:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Paul Cuffee Middle School, Addressing Emotional Needs</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/11/paul-cuffee-middle-school-addressing-emotional-needs.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-11-02T11:59:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-11-02:2012/11/paul-cuffee-middle-school-addressing-emotional-needs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I like this piece in Slate on &lt;a href="http://www.paulcuffee.org"&gt;Paul Cuffee Middle School&lt;/a&gt;, a charter school right here in Providence. Most of what I know about child development seems to suggest that middle schools are sort of ridiculous. At the moment children are looking for role models and close relationships with adults (and not just the kids around them), we decide that kids should have many teachers, teachers should have higher loads, and the kids stay consistent while the adults change&amp;nbsp;constantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, the elementary school model works better for middle school students and vice&amp;nbsp;versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, some research showing K-8 schools have a built-in advantage against the traditional middle&amp;nbsp;school:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://educationnext.org/the-middle-school-plunge/"&gt;The Middle School Plunge&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www0.gsb.columbia.edu/faculty/jrockoff/papers/Rockoff%20Lockwood%20JPubE%202nd%20Revision%20June%202010.pdf"&gt;Stuck in the Middle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more &amp;#8220;popular&amp;#8221; version on Education Next &lt;a href="http://educationnext.org/stuck-in-the-middle/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="charters"></category><category term="edpolicy"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="middle school"></category><category term="providence"></category><category term="rhode island"></category><category term="ri"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on Grit</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/10/thoughts-on-grit.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-01T09:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-10-01:2012/10/thoughts-on-grit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have not had the opportunity to read &lt;a href="http://www.paultough.com/the-books/how-children-succeed/"&gt;Paul Tough&amp;#8217;s newest book&lt;/a&gt; on &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221;&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I have, however, read Paul Tough&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/18/magazine/what-if-the-secret-to-success-is-failure.html"&gt;New York Times Magazine article on grit&lt;/a&gt; and recently listened to an &lt;a href="http://www.econtalk.org/archives/2012/09/paul_tough_on_h.html"&gt;EconTalk podcast&lt;/a&gt; where he discussed &lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;How Children Succeed&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thrust of Tough&amp;#8217;s argument, if I were to be so bold, is that there is a definable set of non-cognitive skills, called &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221;, that are at least as important as academic achievement in determining long-term positive outcomes for kids. Great schools, therefore, would do well to focus on developing these habits as much and as intentionally as they do developing content knowledge and academic prowess. This, according to Tough, is a big part of the &amp;#8220;magic sauce&amp;#8221;&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;of &amp;#8220;No Excuses&amp;#8221; schools like &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KIPP&lt;/span&gt;. They teach &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221; as a part of their intense behavioral management and culture&amp;nbsp;efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Tough is an engaging writer and has a great knack for finding some of the most interesting research not often read in education policy circles, but which is clearly relevant. While listening to the EconLog podcast I found myself often disagreeing with his interpretations/conclusions. But more often, I found myself desperately wishing for a different, slower format because so much of this work begged deeper questioning and conversation. What better reason could there be to buy and read a book-length treatment of these&amp;nbsp;ideas?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I thought I&amp;#8217;d share just a few of my thoughts on &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221; based on this interview and the earlier New York Times Magazine&amp;nbsp;piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teaching conscientiousness in a society that has been so&amp;nbsp;unconscientious&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems fairly obvious that people who don&amp;#8217;t &amp;#8220;play by the rules&amp;#8221; and aren&amp;#8217;t easily motivated to conform to certain habits are less likely to be successful. It is unsurprising that Tough finds research that suggests that there is a &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221; gap between rich and poor. I want to know more about why, and I have, what I hope, is one interesting idea of what contributes to the &amp;#8220;grit&amp;nbsp;gap&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that deterioration of the built environment, especially among the urban and truly rural poor, is a major contributor to low grit. Some parts of this country with high concentrations of poverty look&amp;#8212; bombed out. Roads are littered with deep potholes and scars. The houses have chipped paint, rotting wood exterior elements, and unkept yards. Storefronts were built decades ago on the cheap, aged poorly, and were never updated. Their schools lack good lighting, decent &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HVAC&lt;/span&gt; systems, and functioning toilets. There is no pride found in any of these&amp;nbsp;spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children growing up in poverty do not see neighbors obsessing over their lawn. They do not watch one house after another repaint and reface their exteriors to ensure they weren&amp;#8217;t the ugliest house on the block. They do not see brand new cars, fresh asphalt roads, and schools that resemble palaces. I don&amp;#8217;t think virtually any of this has to do with the people who live in these neighborhoods. I do think it reflects the pathetic state that society has deemed acceptable, so long as it remains sight unseen by those with&amp;nbsp;resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growing up in poverty often means being surrounded by spaces that society has left to rot. How can these children learn conscientiousness when the privileged have been so&amp;nbsp;unconscientious?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The M&amp;amp;M&amp;nbsp;Study&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tough mentions &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1310767/"&gt;a study&lt;/a&gt; where students first take an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IQ&lt;/span&gt; test under normal conditions. These same students are then given an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IQ&lt;/span&gt; test but are rewarded with an M&amp;amp;M each time they get a question right. This tiny immediate incentive resulted in a massive, 1.&lt;span class="caps"&gt;8SD&lt;/span&gt; improvement in mean &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IQ&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;sup id="fnref:0"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:0" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The implications are fascinating. It demonstrates the importance of motivation even while taking a test that is supposedly measuring an intractable, permanent attribute people have. This seems obvious and is fairly well known, but forgotten in many policy circles. I have often lamented that the New England Common Assessment Program has a sizable downward bias when measuring achievement because the exam is low stakes for students. The dramatic decrease in performance observed on the 11th grade &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NECAP&lt;/span&gt; math exam is almost certainly in part due to lower intrinsic motivation amongst high school students compared to their 8th grade and younger&amp;nbsp;selves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some students that have no measurable response to the M&amp;amp;M incentive. These students are exhibiting qualities of Tough&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221;, conscientiousness that leads one to do well simply because they are being measured, or perhaps because there is no reason to do something if it is not going to be done well. I believe that there is also a bias against schools with concentrated poverty because of an uneven distribution of &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212; suburban middle to upper class students with college ambitions will likely be the students who will sit down and try hard on a test just because they are being measured whereas urban students living in poverty are far less likely to exert that same effort for an exercise with no immediate or clear long-term&amp;nbsp;consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this would be pretty blasé were it not for the more distal outcomes observed. The group of students that did not respond to the M&amp;amp;M incentives had significantly and practically better outcomes than those that responded to the incentive. I can&amp;#8217;t recall exactly which outcomes were a part of this study, but Tough cites several independent studies that measure a similar set of qualities and find far better outcomes with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPA&lt;/span&gt;, graduation from high school, post-secondary degree attainment, juvenile delinquency or adult criminal activity, and&amp;nbsp;wages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tough&amp;#8217;s interpretation of these results seems to &lt;a href="http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/2012/09/19/thoughts-on-grading/"&gt;mirror my feelings on grading&lt;/a&gt;. Low stakes testing (or in this case, no-incentive testing) has omitted variable bias which leads to observing students who lack &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221; as lower achieving than they are. The test results are still excellent predictors of later success but lack validity as a pure measure of academic achievement. My complaint about grades that use behavior, attendance, and participation&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;does not stem from their lack of validity at predicting later outcomes. These grades are excellent predictors of later outcomes. Rather, it stems from these grade conflating two very different qualities into a single measure, making it far more difficult to design appropriate interventions and supports that target individual&amp;nbsp;needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tough seems thinks this means that high stakes placed on test scores over emphasizes one quality over the other when both are very important. I disagree. I feel that high stakes test scores recreate the M&amp;amp;M incentive and leads to a better measure of academic ability. That is not to say that we don&amp;#8217;t need to cultivate and measure non-cognitive skills. It just means that trying to measure both at once&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;results in less clear and actionable&amp;nbsp;interpretations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Is the &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221; problem properly described as a failure to recognize long-term&amp;nbsp;benefits?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeatedly both Tough and host Russ Roberts point to the need to provide students who lack grit more information on the long-term benefits of &amp;#8220;doing well&amp;#8221;. For example, Tough cites &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KIPP&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s posting of the economic benefits of a bachelor&amp;#8217;s degree on walls in the halls of their schools as a way to build grit. Somewhat left unsaid is the idea that grit-like behaviors may not describe some kind of &amp;#8220;intrinsic&amp;#8221; motivation, but instead represent an understanding of the long-term extrinsic benefits of certain actions. Grit really means understanding that, &amp;#8220;If I behave appropriately, I will gain the respect of this authority and earn greater autonomy/responsibility,&amp;#8221; or perhaps, &amp;#8220;Doing my homework each night will teach me good habits of work and help me to learn this academic material so I can succeed in college and get a better&amp;nbsp;job.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can grit really be just a heuristic developed to better respond to long-term&amp;nbsp;incentives?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure. I am equally unsure that the activities of a &amp;#8220;No Excuses&amp;#8221; school actually generate the long-term benefits of &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221;. If grit is a powerful heuristic to optimize long-term outcomes, how do we know that many short-term incentives that build behaviors toward academic success mean that students better respond to a broad set of long-term outcomes? Should we believe that behavior bucks/demerit systems, constant small corrections, repeatedly stating the goals of education and its benefits, and other &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KIPP&lt;/span&gt;-like culture-building strategies build a bend toward acting in ways that maximize long-term outcomes? Do students aspire to college because they have internalized its importance, or do the stack of short-term incentives build a desire for sprokets, wignuts, and widgets that just happened to be called a &amp;#8220;bachelor&amp;#8217;s degree&amp;#8221; in this&amp;nbsp;case?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:0"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 79 to 97 according to EconTalk&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:0" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &amp;#8220;grit&amp;#8221; a lot in this post. Please insert quotes each time. It got obnoxious reading it with the quotes actually in place&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My term, not his. Probably stolen from one of my colleagues who uses this term a lot. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;among other non-cognitive, non-academic skills and activities&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or inadvertently measuring both at once, as many low-stakes standardized tests do&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="education"></category><category term="education policy"></category><category term="education reform"></category><category term="grit"></category><category term="paul tough"></category><category term="standardized tests"></category><category term="urban development"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on Grading</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/09/thoughts-on-grading.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-09-19T09:05:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-09-19:2012/09/thoughts-on-grading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/MrPABruno"&gt;Bruno&lt;/a&gt; is a skeptic on &lt;a href="http://scholasticadministrator.typepad.com/thisweekineducation/2012/09/bruno-is-standards-based-grading-a-good-idea.html"&gt;standards-based grading&lt;/a&gt;. He seems to think
that &amp;#8220;mastery of content&amp;#8221; is too abstract for students to work toward
and rightly cites evidence that motivation and changed behavior are
tightly linked to a sense of efficacy, which in turn is tightly linked
to feeling as though you know precisely what to do to get to a
particular&amp;nbsp;outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But isn&amp;#8217;t mastery of content essentially, &amp;#8220;Do well on your assignments
and tests&amp;#8221;? And while a massive, standards-based report card may be hard
for a parent to read, is it any more confusing than seeing awful results
on standardized tests and a student who clearly doesn&amp;#8217;t read on
grade-level receive good grades because of participation, attendance,
and behavior? As a parent, how do you know to intercede on your child&amp;#8217;s
behalf when you see a &amp;#8220;B&amp;#8221; which actually represents a C- on content
knowledge and skills and an A+ for effort, behavior, and&amp;nbsp;completion?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I am against including behavior, attendance, and effort as a
part of the same grade as academics. I think there needs to be a clear
place to present evidence of academic ability and growth independent of
behavioral growth. Both are important, and while linked, are certainly
not moving in lockstep for the typical child. Accurate information in
both domains is far better than falsely presenting a singular, mixed-up
&amp;#8220;truth&amp;#8221; about a child&amp;#8217;s success in&amp;nbsp;school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the same reason I am not a fan of school report cards with a single
letter grade rating, I am not for just a single letter grade for
students. Ultimately, they both represent poor combinations of data that
obscure more than they&amp;nbsp;reveal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing report cards or &amp;#8220;grading&amp;#8221; systems, both for program
evaluation and for students, always conjures one of the few concepts I
recall from linear algebra. It seems to me that any good grading system
should provide a basis, that is, a minimal set of linearly independent
vectors which, via linear combination, can describe an entire vector
space. Remove the jargon and you&amp;#8217;re left&amp;nbsp;with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measure the least amount of unrelated things possible that, taken
together, describe all there is to know about what you are&amp;nbsp;measuring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single grade that combines all the effort, behavior, attendance, and
various unrelated academic standards I might get an overall description
that says &amp;#8220;round&amp;#8221;. But by separating out the data at some other level,
the picture might describe a golf ball and its dimples, a baseball and
its stitches, or a soccer ball with its hexagon-pentagon&amp;nbsp;pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we need to find a way to let people know what kind of ball they&amp;nbsp;have.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bruno"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="grading"></category><category term="grading policy"></category><category term="twie"></category></entry><entry><title>Social Promotion, Tutoring, and Funding</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/02/social-promotion-tutoring-and-funding.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-02-15T09:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-02-15:2012/02/social-promotion-tutoring-and-funding.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_promotion"&gt;Social promotion&lt;/a&gt;, in education circles, refers to the practice of allowing students to move on to the next grade level or course even though they are unable to demonstrate they have mastered the skills and knowledge they were expected to learn. Ending or reducing social promotion has been a major theme in the standards-based education reform of the last 10-15 years. Ending social promotion feels like a sound, obvious consequence of standards-based education. Each year (or course) comes with set of standards that articulate what students must know and be able to do once complete. Since the standards of the following course will assume proficiency on previous standards, there is a fundamental common sense to prohibiting students to move to the next level before they have conquered all prior&amp;nbsp;levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, this is a gross oversimplification bordering on &lt;em&gt;reductio ad absurdum&lt;/em&gt;. Allow me to throw a few wrinkles into the carrion calls for social promotion&amp;#8217;s demise. First, some standards do not come packaged with lofty presumptions of prior knowledge or skills. For example, a student could be quite successful in a high school chemistry or physics course without being successful in biology. In fact many students take these three courses in a sequence which explicitly prevents taking advantage of the natural interrelatedness of these sciences&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. For sure there are some skills that serve as critical gateways to future standards and expectations, but a student may fail a course while still having all of the core scaffolding in place for the next course level. Second, it is unclear that repeating a class (or entire grade-level) is an effective mechanism to successfully attain acceptable achievement. What proportion of content that will be repeated has a student already successfully learned without need for reinforcement? Are the strategies and pedagogy employed to teach students new material the same as those used to re-teach material? I&amp;#8217;m doubtful. Then there are behavioral and social concerns. What are the impacts on a student&amp;#8217;s self-esteem? What are the impacts, particularly in elementary schools, of mixing students at even greater age ranges? If students must relearn content, reread the same books, etc, what will happen to their level of engagement with the material? What is the impact of isolating students from their friends in a way that might feel like&amp;nbsp;punishment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s research on both sides of this issue&amp;#8212; some that demonstrates that students who are held back &lt;a href="http://www.mitpressjournals.org/doi/pdf/10.1162/edfp.2007.2.4.319"&gt;do better academically&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and some that show outcomes are no better or worse. The impact on the socio-emotional side also seems mixed, although there is more consensus around negative consequences for being held back. That being said, much of the research I have read on social promotion looks at all students being held back in various contexts and not specifically examining long-term effects within a large-scale implementation that regularizes the process, which perhaps decreases the social stigma of being held back and increases the efficacy of teachers with held back students. I am having a hard time remembering at the moment, but I can&amp;#8217;t recall a large-scale study that used regression discontinuity (and instrumental variable) like the previously linked Jay P. Greene Florida study that took a robust look at socio-economic outcomes. Less rigorous methodologies may introduce substantial bias to results&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I generally think that social promotion is not ideal. In a perfect world, principals and district leaders would have a better sense of how well teachers are able to differentiate instruction in their classrooms more precisely. This way, they could adequately determine when a student is so far behind expectations that it is unreasonable to expect teachers to deliver the necessary instruction in a mixed-ability classroom. When a student is that far behind at the end of the school year, targeted summer intervention would attempt to bring a student to within an acceptable range by the start of the next school year. If this fails, then, and only then, should a student be held&amp;nbsp;back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is new. In fact, Wikipedia led me to an &lt;a href="http://www2.ed.gov/pubs/socialpromotion/intro.html"&gt;article about social promotion&lt;/a&gt; archived on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; Department of Education webpage from May 1999 that is strikingly similar to everything I wrote above&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richardson has a great post in &lt;a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/national/archive/2012/02/closing-the-literacy-gap-the-trouble-with-holding-back-students/253065/"&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;about an intriguing alternative. &lt;a href="https://webapp4.asu.edu/directory/person/28597"&gt;David Berliner&lt;/a&gt;, an Arizona State University professor of education,&amp;nbsp;says,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Everybody supports the idea that if a student isn&amp;#8217;t reading well in
third grade that it&amp;#8217;s a signal that the child needs help. If you hold
them back, you&amp;#8217;re going to spend roughly another \&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(10,000 per child
for an extra year of schooling. If you spread out that \\)&lt;/span&gt;10,000 over
the fourth and fifth grades for extra tutoring, in the long run you&amp;#8217;re
going to get a better&amp;nbsp;outcome.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has recently been an increase in &lt;a href="http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/fryer/files/charter_school_strategies.pdf"&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; about the efficacy of intensive, very small group (like two-on-one) tutoring at raising academic achievement based on a &amp;#8220;successful replication&amp;#8221; of the &lt;a href="http://www.matchschool.org/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MATCH&lt;/span&gt; Charter School&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; tutoring program in the &lt;a href="http://www.houstonisd.org/"&gt;Houston Independent School District&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.houstonisd.org/HISDConnectDS/v/index.jsp?vgnextoid=436bcd7298b69210VgnVCM10000028147fa6RCRD"&gt;Apollo 20&lt;/a&gt; Program&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Intensive one-on-one support has several key advantages that address some of my &amp;#8220;wrinkles&amp;#8221; about social promotion above. The instruction is specifically catered toward the exact standards that a student is weak on (and possibly on standards that are more foundational to future learning). The strategies and techniques used to teach a student may not be the same as whole-classroom, first-time exposure learning. The intervention strategy feels more like a surplus than deficit-driven policy, i.e. students are receiving &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; because of their achievement not being &amp;#8220;punished&amp;#8221;. And that is not remotely an exhaustive&amp;nbsp;list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that education funding is not structured to spend the way that Berliner is recommending. Revenues are often raised or doled out on a per pupil basis so holding a student for an extra year will virtually automatically result in additional formula-driven dollars&lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:7" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. There is no way to flag a student as needing the &amp;#8220;5th-year high school&amp;#8221; funding now, in the form of two years of intensive, one-on-one tutoring in elementary or middle school. I am not sure I think that&amp;#8217;s a good thing, because I really do think that Berliner is on to something here. The cost-effectiveness of the total investment in any one student identified as being at risk of falling seriously behind is likely to be far higher providing a huge influx of resources to be used entirely on individualized intervention rather than offering an entire extra year of education overall and repeating a specific&amp;nbsp;grade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logistics of supporting this kind of intervention with anything but local or private revenue is causing my brain to do mental gymnastics, but the complexity might really be worth the&amp;nbsp;benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An aside for another day. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ending social promotion based on standardized assessments offers pretty much a textbook example of regression discontinuity studies, which I think is kind of cool&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although woefully outdated and using a source from 1986, the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grade_retention#Research"&gt;research section of the Wikipedia page on grade retention&lt;/a&gt; outlines this in effective and simple language&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did find the article after I wrote this post&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And on her blog, The Educated Reporter&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course there is lot of past research to support this idea, but I do think that &lt;a href="http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/fryer"&gt;Fryer&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s Apollo 20 evaluation has reinvigorated discussion around the effectiveness of this type of intervention in the past several months. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, at least. Of course many states are reducing their state aid formula in funky ways and there are loopholes in most maintenance of effort laws that are now being rigorously used to allow for per pupil decreases in local revenues&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = '//cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: 'center'," +
        "    displayIndent: '0em'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'black ! important'} }" +
        "    } " +
        "}); ";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="cost-benefit analysis"></category><category term="edpolicy"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="education funding"></category><category term="efficiency"></category><category term="intervention"></category><category term="MATCH"></category><category term="social promotion"></category><category term="standards-based reform"></category><category term="tutoring"></category></entry><entry><title>What if the technology revolution in schools is really about the simple stuff?</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/01/what-if-the-technology-revolution-in-schools-is-really-about-the-simple-stuff.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-18T22:23:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-01-18:2012/01/what-if-the-technology-revolution-in-schools-is-really-about-the-simple-stuff.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The complicated school day is essentially designed so the minimum number of staff are away from kids at any given time. Some folks are trying to combat this with &lt;a href="http://www.allthingsplc.info/pdf/articles/make_time_for_collaboration.pdf"&gt;common planning time&lt;/a&gt; and other &lt;a href="http://www.erstools.org/Dream/district_es_a.cfm"&gt;scheduling gymnastics&lt;/a&gt;. These attempts are up against a strong opposing priority&amp;#8212; students must be with an adult essentially 100% of the time. Not only that, but the middle of a hectic day focused on teaching is not really conducive to reflection, strategizing, and deep planning on a tight schedule. The temptation to use this precious time to put out the days (or weeks) fires instead of the kind of collaboration and professional learning desired is just too&amp;nbsp;strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And quite honestly, I think teachers should get space in the day to vent, grade papers, setup their classroom, call parents, and do all the normal &amp;#8220;maintenance&amp;#8221; required to keep their classes running. The question then remains, how do we create this dynamic space for professional learning, coordination of services, collaboration on lesson delivery, creative thinking about school structures,&amp;nbsp;etc?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really think that &lt;a href="http://www.storiesfromschool.org/travis.html"&gt;Travis&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="http://www.storiesfromschool.org/"&gt;Stories from School&lt;/a&gt; has it right: &lt;a href="http://www.storiesfromschool.rg/2012/01/not-meeting.html"&gt;use technology to make it easy for teachers, administrators, and other staff to communicate and coordinate&lt;/a&gt;. There is no shortage of snake oil peddled to &amp;#8220;solve&amp;#8221; education in America and one of the most persistent memes is the technological revolution will alter classrooms forever. Technology&amp;#8217;s real promise is in &lt;em&gt;schools&lt;/em&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;classrooms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Sharing assessment results and lesson plans, coordinating with interventions being offered to a student, talking to other teachers who have or have had the same student, and more can all be made much easier with technology. Rather than finding the time to meet face-to-face, faculty members can put energy into building relationships around teaching and learning when they have the time. The opportunity to breakaway the time constraints typically placed on synchronous conversation is huge. The opportunity for rich asynchronous sharing is virtually brand new.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;I do not want this to sound like pushing for &amp;#8220;social media&amp;#8221; for teachers, mostly because the technological innovations involved are not a part of the current flavor of Web 2.0 networking. Even the old tools like email, instant messaging, and perhaps the oldest social tool of all, discussion boards, could be extremely helpful for&amp;nbsp;folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is new, most of this has been said, yet it seems like too few schools have found a way to leverage existing and inexpensive technology to implement this kind of communication as an essential part of work culture. That seems like a massive missed opportunity that should not be lost while district officials are distracted by quick-and-dirty 4 week online courses for credit&amp;nbsp;recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons I&amp;#8217;m not optimistic on technology revolutionizing the classroom. My preferred explanation is that the &lt;em&gt;technology of learning has not changed, &lt;/em&gt;not to be confused with the technology of human machines, but instead the technology of &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; human machine. Human learning is no different from it was in the past so our technology can only promise new delivery mechanisms for the same thousands of years old approach to teaching and learning. Education can gain efficiencies in delivery that are not to be underestimated. But I think of a revolution as changing a process so dramatically that an observer would barely recognize the process a decade later. The computers and the internet have certainly done that in some fields, but I don&amp;#8217;t see this happening in schools.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so I guess teachers could leave a flyer in mailboxes in the past, but come on&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="cpt"></category><category term="edtech"></category><category term="education"></category></entry><entry><title>Associated Press: Israeli schools not looking so good against OECD peers.</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/01/associated-press-israeli-schools-not-looking-so-good-against-oecd-peers.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-07T10:10:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2012-01-07:2012/01/associated-press-israeli-schools-not-looking-so-good-against-oecd-peers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I read an interesting &lt;a href="http://goo.gl/SSY83"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; this morning on Israeli
schools. Facing extreme poverty among Arab-Israeli&amp;#8217;s and the
ultra-orthodox, Israel struggles to maintain three separate school
systems and succeed. It reminded me of some interesting centralized
policy reforms in Israel that have led to great natural experiments. For
example, so-called Maimonides Laws which capped class sizes at 40,
allowed for some really interesting regression-discontinuity studies on
the impact of class size &lt;sup id="fnref:classsize"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:classsize" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I found most interesting in this article, however, was the point
made by Jon&amp;nbsp;Medved:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While agreeing Israeli schools need to raise their standards,
technology entrepreneur Jon Medved doesn&amp;#8217;t think Israel&amp;#8217;s test scores
tell the whole story. He says informal education, through the
military, youth movements, and extracurricular activities, builds
skills. He also praised programs for gifted&amp;nbsp;children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, Medved says he isn&amp;#8217;t worried that Israel&amp;#8217;s tech-driven
economy will slide because of deficiencies in the school&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;While I think it&amp;#8217;s important to sound alarm signals, I haven&amp;#8217;t heard
from tech companies &amp;#8230; &amp;#8216;the employees we&amp;#8217;re getting are not
educated,&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221; Medved&amp;nbsp;said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two thoughts came to mind. First, we certainly are hearing in the United
States that employers are unhappy with the caliber of candidates for
open positions. It&amp;#8217;s unclear that in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; this is a result of low
aggregate skills or just tremendous mismatch between the skills that are
attained and the skills that are now valued in the marketplace. Second,
Israel&amp;#8217;s universal military service provides several additional years of
intense training and skill attainment even before college. Considering
the broad range of roles one can take on in the state military ((For
example, social workers in Israel are basically military trained, given
job experience, and then set out without a need for 5 years of
schooling, although I believe many do receive at least a bachelor&amp;#8217;s)),
it&amp;#8217;s hard not to see Israel&amp;#8217;s mandatory service as a massive vocational
educational&amp;nbsp;program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t have much analysis here, but mandatory public/civil service is
an interesting concept that this article will keep me thinking about
over the&amp;nbsp;weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:classsize"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/staiger/files/AngristLavy%&lt;span class="caps"&gt;2BQJE&lt;/span&gt;%2B1999.pdf;
Angrist has also done several other studies in Israel with Lavy, a nice
little summary of which is available here http://www.nber.org/reporter/summer03/angrist.html&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:classsize" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Angrist"></category><category term="class_size_reduction"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="Israel"></category><category term="military"></category></entry><entry><title>Justin Baeder asks the Wrong Question on Teacher Evaluation</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2011/09/justin-baeder-asks-the-wrong-question-on-teacher-evaluation.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-09-16T22:48:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2011-09-16:2011/09/justin-baeder-asks-the-wrong-question-on-teacher-evaluation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re interested in education, I highly recommend Justin Baeder&amp;#8217;s&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;#8221;&lt;a href="http://blogs.edweek.org/edweek/on_performance/"&gt;On Performance&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; blog hosted over on Education&amp;nbsp;Week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, he ended his &lt;a href="http://blogs.edweek.org/edweek/on_performance/2011/09/are_we_expecting_too_much_of_teacher_evaluation_systems.html"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; with a question, &amp;#8220;I would be very interested to learn of any other sector that has achieved substantial performance gains by reforming its evaluation processes. We&amp;#8217;re putting a lot of eggs in the &amp;#8216;improve teacher evaluation to improve student learning&amp;#8217; basket, but no one even seems to be asking whether this strategy has any&amp;nbsp;merit.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is the write idea but the wrong question. What we should wonder is whether any other sector has achieved substantial performance gains by reforming its entire process for hiring, retaining, supporting, and terminating its employees when that sector started with an extremely rigid, non-differentiated structure. Teacher evaluation is about providing better professional growth opportunities targeted to an individual&amp;#8217;s needs. It&amp;#8217;s about rewarding folks who are doing a stellar job and making sure that you can reward mission-critical people who might otherwise leave for other opportunities. And, much to many union members&amp;#8217; chagrin, it&amp;#8217;s also about providing substantial a substantial and trusted evidence base that principals can turn to justify termination&amp;nbsp;decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask your favorite policy professional or administrator why they are pushing for centralized, mandatory, and prescriptive forms of teacher evaluation. I can guarantee they&amp;#8217;ll include the current lack of serious evaluation in schools. I would bet that most folks also are pushing for these policies as a proactive step to make sure they can win union-based challenges against performance-based terminations and reassignment. Because the teacher unions are so strong and are largely steadfast in their need to treat all teachers equally&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, policymakers feel like they have to wrap evaluations in as much novel social science and standardization as possible so that they have even the tiniest chance in hell of holding up in court. To what extent can the lack of robust evaluation be connected to school leaders&amp;#8217; lack of self-efficacy for action on this&amp;nbsp;information?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teachers fear that a world without these protections would produce unfair evaluations and termination procedures that are subjective. Secretly, I bet that most policymakers would be totally comfortable not pushing hard for value-added models and overly specific observation rubrics. So long as they felt confident they could take action in response to the evaluations, the current evaluation hawks would instead be willing to leave much more to individual professional judgment&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. If the primary relationship in a school building was professional, and not a unionized labor-management split, a lot of the current evaluation policy might not be necessary. In the very least, the policies could be less centralized. But ultimately, professionals are held accountable for their work quality by bosses that employees respect as&amp;nbsp;professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll end with one final thought: I wonder what the teacher evaluation narrative would be like in an alternative history where there was no split between the teacher unions and professional organizations of education administrators and&amp;nbsp;professors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Important note: while I do work at a state department of education, I am not directly involved in nor am I intimately familiar with our teacher evaluation model or policies. As an employee of the Rhode Island Department of Education, I am also a member of the American Federation of Teachers Local 2012 union. The thoughts I&amp;#8217;ve expressed in this post are entirely my own and does not represent the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AFT&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIDE&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;position.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Per his EdWeek Bio, &amp;#8220;Justin Baeder is a public school principal in Seattle and a doctoral student studying principal performance and productivity at the University of Washington. In this blog he aims to examine issues of performance, improvement, and the changing nature of the education profession.&amp;#8221; &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I&amp;#8217;ll write about the irony of equality of treatment for education professionals. It&amp;#8217;s strange that our thinking around funding has largely evolved from &amp;#8220;equality&amp;#8221; to &amp;#8220;adequacy&amp;#8221; but not our treatment of adults&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related important issue to solve&amp;#8212; low principal quality undermines this possibility. One day I&amp;#8217;ll write about my belief that the principal role is poorly designed and dooms most people to failure. Rethinking the building principal is a critical structural reform folks will be hearing more and more about&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="education"></category><category term="evaluation"></category><category term="public-sector unions"></category><category term="teacher evaluation"></category><category term="union"></category></entry></feed>