<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>jasonpbecker</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.jsonbecker.com/</id><updated>2013-08-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Some Changes for Rhode Island State Aid to Education</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2013/08/some-changes-for-rhode-island-state-aid-to-education.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason P. Becker</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2013-08-22:2013/08/some-changes-for-rhode-island-state-aid-to-education.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In December 2009, the education department head, Professor Kenneth K. Wong, another graduate student and myself were part of a three-person team consulting the Rhode Island Department of Education (RIDE) on how to establish a new state funding formula. We worked with finance and legal staff at the department to develop the legislation for the 2010 session that would establish a state funding formula for the first time in 15 years.
 
The Board of Regents had already passed a resolution with its policy priorities that they wanted enshrined in the formula. Additionally, there had been many attempts over the past 5-10 years to pass a new formula that failed for various reasons, chief among them that all previously proposed formulas were accompanied with a call to increase state funding for education 30-50%, with some even envisioning nearly doubling the state education funding. Our task was to research funding formulas, both in practice in other states and in the literature research on school finance, and achieve the goals of the Board of Regents without proposing a mammoth increase in state aid that would sink the entire endeavor &lt;sup id="fnref:increase"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:increase" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The general sense was that while more state aid had the potential to improve the progressiveness of education expenditures, the reality is the overall spending level in Rhode Island is high, and introducing new money was less important than redistributing state aid. I share this belief, particularly because I think adding money to the right places is simple once there is already a way to equitably distribute those funds. Tying up the increase in funding alongside a distribution method is a recipe for political horse-trading that can result in all kinds of distortions that prevent aid from flowing where needed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My role in this process was primarily to create Excel simulators that would allow us to immediately track the impacts of changing different parts of the formula. I also helped RIDE staff interpret the meaning of changes to the math behind the funding formula and understand what levers existed to change the formula and how these changes impacted both the resulting distribution and policy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had three months. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of people who are unhappy about the results of the formula that ultimately passed in June 2010. Because we are redistributing essentially the same amount of state aid, there are some districts that are losing money while others are gaining funds &lt;sup id="fnref:holdharmless"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:holdharmless" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Some dislike the fact that we used only a "weight" for free and reduced price lunch status. Alternative formulas (and formulas in other states) typically include numerous weights, from limited English proficiency and special education status, to gifted and talented and career and technical education &lt;sup id="fnref:ajello"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:ajello" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. And yet others were displeased that many costs, including transportation and facilities maintenance, were excluded from the state-base of education aid. Then there are those who think the transition is all off-- five years is too long to wait to get the increases the formula proposes, and ten years is far too fast to lose the money the formula proposes.[^transition] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Good State Aid System&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I am proud of the formula produced for several reasons. 
First, it passed successfully and has been fully funded (and sometimes more than fully funded) each year of implementation throughout a period of massive structural budget deficits. This is no small accomplishment. The advocacy community rightfully pushes us to build ideal systems, but in our role of policy entrepreneurs we are faced with the reality that a policy that does not become law and is not supported as law may as well not exist. Producing a formula that has some of the other positive qualities discussed below, passing that formula, and implementing the formula with little fanfare is not a small accomplishment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the formula is highly progressive, sending as much as 20 times more aid to some of our poorest communities in Rhode Island compared to the wealthiest. I am not positive how this compares to other states-- that's a topic I certainly want to work on for a future post-- but with just 39 cities and towns, it seems to show a high preference for &lt;em&gt;vertical equity&lt;/em&gt;, treating different cities and towns differently. There are communities on both ends of the distribution who want substantially more state funding, and our state aid formula is not sufficient to effectively crowd out local capacity for education spending and ensure that our poorest communities are spending more than our wealthier ones &lt;sup id="fnref:comparative"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:comparative" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but it's a very strong start. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the formula is relatively simple. While I do not necessarily agree that it is a virtue to have fewer weights and a simple formula in perpetuity, the experience with other states and other formula-based programs show that weights and complexities are very easy to add and very hard to take away. Once a particular policy preference is enshrined in the distribution method, it had better be right because a community of advocacy will maintain that weight long into the future. Personally, I felt it critical to start with the very simple "core" formula that could be adjusted over time. I have some ideas on how I might modify/add to this core that I will be sharing in this post, but I firmly believe that starting with a simple core was the right move. It is also worth noting that because of the need to ensure the transition is smoothed out so that gains in some districts equal the total losses in the others meant that even a more progressive weighting scheme would not impact school funding until the far back end of the transition period (which we proposed as 7 years but was pushed to 5 years during the legislative process), since communities were already gaining funds as fast as we could move them. For this reason, not only was a simple core preferable from my technocratic perspective, but it also was not likely to have any immediate downside. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fourth, we removed the long-term regionalization bonuses. Rhode Island had sought to reduce the ridiculous number of school districts by providing a bonus for regionalizing in the early 90s. Unfortunately, because of the timing of the abandonment of the previous state aid formula, the districts that did choose to regionalize had their base funding locked in at a level 6-8% higher than it should have been, because they were receiving a bonus that was meant to fade away over the course of several years. I could justify a small increase in state funding to pay some of the transition expenses of regionalizing districts, but long term funding increases? Part of the goal of regionalization is the reduction of overhead that allows for decreased costs (or increased services at the same costs). There is no ongoing need to supply a massive state bonus for regionalizing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now just because I am proud of this work does not mean that I think we have "solved" education funding in Rhode Island. Personally, I believe there are other defensible ways to distribute funding in Rhode Island, each of which represents slightly different policy preferences. There is no hard and fast "right" or "wrong" way to do this, within certain guidelines. As I see it, so long as the formula is progressive and moving toward a greater chance of seeing a day where Providence has the highest paid staff in the state &lt;sup id="fnref:comparative"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:comparative" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, we are on the right path. I don't believe that Rhode Island will have a truly "great" education finance climate without a substantial growth in the economy or a huge new tax that dramatically lowers the ability of municipalities to generate school funding while bolstering state aid. However, I think we have a great foundation and a "good" system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the remainder of this post, I would like to propose a few ideas that could help move Rhode Island from "good" to "very good" that I think are feasible within the next five years &lt;sup id="fnref:goodtogreat"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:goodtogreat" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Very Good State Aid Program&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a little over three years since its establishment, I think we are ready to tackle several additional aspects of state education funding in Rhode Island. One thing you may notice is that few of these ideas impact the original formula. Part of why that is comes from my aforementioned preference for a simple formula, and part is because these include some non-formula issues that were not pursued in 2010 in an effort to keep the focus on the main policy matters. 
First, and perhaps the most consequential change that can be made to state funding, is the teacher pension fund payments. Currently, the state and local districts split the cost of teacher pension contributions 60/40. This is a flat split, regardless of the wealth of the community. I think it's absurd to ignore community wealth for such a large portion of state education expenditures. Using the Adjusted Equalized Weighted Assessment Values (AEWAV) to determine the reimbursement rates would be a big improvement on the progressiveness of school funding. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I would make a slight change to the way that we fund charter schools. When we were developing the formula, there was broad agreement among policymakers that the "money should follow the child". In one sense, this is the system we proposed since school district funding is based on enrollments. However, I think an irrational desire to not "double count" students, alongside the need to keep funding as flat as possible, pushed the formula a bit too far when it comes to charters. The old way of funding charter schools allowed districts to hold back 5% of the total per pupil expenditure from their charter school tuitions. This meant charter schools received 5% less funding than traditional public schools, but it also recognized that there are some fixed costs in districts that are not immediately recoverable when students leave on the margins. I think the state should return to this practice, however only if the state is willing to pay the withheld 5% to charters. I do think its fair to take into account some fixed costs, but I don't believe it's fair that charter schools received less funding as a result. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, we excluded all building maintenance costs from the base amount of state aid. This was largely because the formula was supposed to represent only the marginal instructional costs associated with each student. I don't necessarily think that these costs have to be added into the base amount. However, I would like to see the state contribute to the maintenance of buildings more directly. I think the state should provide a flat dollar amount, say $100,000, per building in each district, provided that key criteria are met. The buildings should be at 90% occupancy/utilization, should have a minimum size set based on the research on efficiency (roughly 300 students at the elementary level and 600 students for high schools), and there should be some minimum standard for building systems quality and upkeep. These requirements are mostly about making sure this flat fund, which is really about the fixed costs of maintaining buildings, doesn't create incentives to build more. It may seem inconsequential, but I think it's important to state the preference for well-sized, occupied &lt;sup id="fnref:occupied"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:occupied" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and maintained buildings is worthwhile. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's wrong that the minimum reimbursement rate for school construction aid was raised to 40% during the funding formula debates in the General Assembly. This amounts to a massive subsidy for suburban schools and the previous 30% minimum is part of why we have such stark facilities inequities in the state. We should remove the minimums on construction reimbursement and simply use AEWAV to determine the reimbursement rate. Also, we need to establish a revolving facilities loan fund, much like the one used for sewers (and now &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/2013/03/21/ricwfa-explainer/"&gt;roads and bridges&lt;/a&gt;). Access to lower interest bonds should not be dependent on city finances. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing we did not include in the original funding formula that has come under considerably criticism is a special weight for students who are labeled English language learners. There are a few reasons we made this decision. The districts that have ELLs are the same districts that have high levels of poverty. In fact, the 5 communities that had more than 5% of their students classified as ELLs were, in order, also the top five districts with regards to free and reduced price lunch eligibility. Combined with a transition plan that was already increasing funding to these districts as rapidly as could be afforded, there were virtually no short-term consequences of not including an ELL weight. It's worth noting that formula dollars are not categorical funds-- there are no restrictions on how districts should spend this money, and there are no guarantees that an ELL weight would have any impact on ELL spending. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were also concerned with incentivizing over-identification and failing to exit students who should no longer be classified as ELLs. I am also personally concerned with mistaking the additional supports we want to target as needed for English language acquisition; it would not only inspire the wrong policies and supports for these students, but it fails to recognize a host of needs that persist for these students well beyond English acquisition. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the funding formula hearings at House and Senate Finance Committees we discussed the need for further study on this issue. I think that the next weight in the formula should be based on the Census and American Communities Survey. By using these data sets, classification of students who are eligible for the weight would not be dependent on the school district itself. Rather than focus on child language acquisition, I think we should broaden this weight to be applied based on the percentage of households that speak a language other than English in the home, where English is spoken at a level below "very well" &lt;sup id="fnref:technical"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:technical" rel="footnote"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This would ensure that students who live in language minority households receive additional supports throughout their education, regardless of their language acquisition status. I would make this weight lower than some in the literature because it would apply to a broader set of students, probably somewhere around 40% like the poverty weight. For reference, the latest five-year estimate from the ACS data shows that 24.3% of households fit this definition in the city of Providence. With a 40% weight, at 22,500 students, with a foundation amount of around $9,000 per student, this weight would increase funding to Providence by a little over $16,000,000. Similar to other formula aid, these funds would be unrestricted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while I think that $16,000,000 is no small potatoes, and I am happy to express our policy preference to drive funding into communities where families are not using English in the home, some perspective is warranted. Providence will receive almost $240,000,000 in state aid when the formula is fully transitioned, compared to about $190,000,000 before. Adding this weight would only represent a 6% increase in state aid from the full formula amount. It's an important increase, but I hope you'll forgive me if I felt it was not grossly unfair to exclude it in the first iteration of the funding formula, especially considering we still have not fully transitioned to those higher dollar amounts sent to districts that would benefit from these funds. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;It Takes Money&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these recommendations, in my view, would improve the way that Rhode Island distributes education aid. Some of the changes are technical, others address areas that are currently not considered, and some are purely about increasing the progressiveness of aid. All of these changes will require an even greater state contribution to education aid, but these increases would be an order of magnitude lower than what it would take to increase the state aid to covering 50-60% of all education expenditures. While I would support some pretty radical changes to drive more money into the state aid system, I think that each of these improvements are worth doing on the path to increased aid. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:increase"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should note, that few people I spoke to were not in favor of raising the amount of state aid. We all want more money to come from the state because those dollars are far more progressive. However, Rhode Island was deep in its recession at this point in time and the dollar amounts to make a real dent in the state to local share in education are just staggering. Rhode Island currently funds just short of 40% of total school expenditures at the state level. To increase that to 60%, which is closer to the national average, they would have to contribute $500M more-- a roughly 60% increase from the current level. Just for some context, the main tax fight of Rhode Island progressives has been to repeal tax cuts for higher income individuals that were instituted starting in 2006 in an attempt to move toward a flat income tax rate in Rhode Island. The impact of this repeal would be an increase in revenues that would cover roughly 10% of the increase in school funding required to move from 40% to 60% state aid. Of course, those dollars are supposed to pay for some portion of restoring pension benefits, so it's already spoken for.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:increase" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:holdharmless"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hold harmless provisions, when introduced in other states, serve to dramatically distort the redistributive properties of state aid and almost always require a huge influx of funds. In fact, a hold harmless provision in Rhode Island would have required a doubling of state aid, which ultimately would have guaranteed that wealthy communities continue to receive too much state aid while less wealthy communities are stuck fighting year after year for tremendous revenue increases through taxation just to get their fair share. Essentially, hold harmless would ensure that you never reach formula-level spending and guarantee that state aid would not be very progressive.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:holdharmless" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:ajello"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One very popular progressive member of the Rhode Island General Assembly had been working for years to pass a new funding formula and had five or six such weights in her version. Interestingly, with the glaring exception of sending $0 to Newport in state aid, the difference in the overall distribution of funds by district in Rhode Island using this formula and our formula was tiny, almost always &amp;lt;5%.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:ajello" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:transitions"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smoothing the "gains" and "losses" overtime was important to keep the formula as close to revenue neutral as possible. Of course, there are increases due to inflation and other factors each year as a part of the base, but our goal was to truly redistribute the funds such that not only is the end number not a big increase in total state aid but that getting through the transition period did not have huge costs. If it did, there is no way we could feel confident we would ever reach the point where the formula actually dictated state aid, much like the hold harmless provision prevents a full transition. Modeling various transition plans was a nightmare for me.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:transitions" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:comparative"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people forget that education spending is about competition within a single market. Overall spending matters less within this market than how you spend compared to others. The trick is that an urban school primarily working with traditionally under served families needs to be able to pay not just for more material supplies, but mostly for higher quality teachers and staff (and perhaps quantity). Because of compensating wage differentials, even hiring teachers and staff that are the same quality as wealthy communities costs more.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:comparative" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:goodtogreat"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I will write a future post on some ideas of how to push Rhode Island to "great", even though I view all of those solutions as politically impossible.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:goodtogreat" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:occupied"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would include any leased space as occupied. We should encourage full utilization of the buildings, whether that includes charter schools, central office use, city government, or private companies. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:occupied" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:technical"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This definition is clunky, but its how the ACS and Census track these things. This definition is clunky, but its how the ACS and Census track these things. We could verify the data using the data reported by districts about language spoken in the home. I would recommend using this data point to assist with whether or not to include these weights for charter schools. For example, approximately half of those families that do not speak English in the home also speak English very poorly. Therefore, I might apply half of the weight to each individual child whose family reports speaking a language other than English at home. Of course, the actual proportion of the weight should be specific to the ratio of speakers of language other than English to non-very well speakers of English by community.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:technical" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>What can be done for Rhode Island Pensioners?</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2013/08/what-can-be-done-for-rhode-island-pensioners.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason P. Becker</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2013-08-15:2013/08/what-can-be-done-for-rhode-island-pensioners.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post originally appeared on my old blog on January 2, 2013 but did not make the transition to this site due to error. I decided to repost it with a new date after recovering it from a cached version on the web.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rhode Island &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/2011/11/17/analysis-why-rhode-island-passed-pension-reform-in-2011/"&gt;passed sweeping pension reform last fall&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/2011/11/21/union-email-blasts-dems-on-pension-law-previews-legal-fight/"&gt;angering&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/2012/02/07/unions-to-ri-negotiate-a-pension-deal-before-you-lose-in-court/"&gt;major labor unions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.rifuture.org/tag/pension"&gt;progressives&lt;/a&gt; throughout the state. These reforms have &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/2011/10/24/moodys-raimondo-chafee-pension-bill-good-for-rhode-island/"&gt;significantly decreased both the short and long-run costs to the state&lt;/a&gt;, while &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/2011/11/17/ri-lawmakers-ok-historic-pension-overhaul-by-wide-margins/"&gt;decreasing the benefits of both current and future retirees&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the &lt;a href="http://blogs.wpri.com/2011/09/16/raimondo-chafee-set-to-freeze-colas-put-all-in-hybrid-plan/"&gt;most controversial measures&lt;/a&gt; in the pension reform package was suspending annual raises &lt;sup id="fnref:raises"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:raises" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for current retirees. I have noticed two main critiques of this element. The first criticism was that ending this practice constitutes a decrease in benefits to existing retirees who did not consent to these changes, constituting a breach of contract and assault on property rights. This critique is outside of the scope of this post. What I would like to address is the second criticism, that annual raises are critical to retirement security due to inflation, especially for the most vulnerable pensioners who earn near-poverty level wages from their pensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I am broadly supportive of the changes made to the pension system in Rhode Island, I also believe that it is important to recognize the differential impact suspending annual raises has on a retired statehouse janitor who currently earns \$22,000 a year from their pension and a former state department director earning \$70,000 a year from their pension. Protecting the income of those most vulnerable to inflation is a worthy goal &lt;sup id="fnref:worthy"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:worthy" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a simple recommendation that I think can have a substantial, meaningful impact on the most vulnerable retirees at substantially less cost than annual raises. This recommendation will be attractive to liberals and conservatives, as well as the “business elite” that have long called for increasing Rhode Island’s competitiveness with neighboring states. It is time that Rhode Island leaves the company of just three other states– Minnesota, Nebraska, and Vermont– that have no tax exemptions for retirement income &lt;sup id="fnref:exemptions"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:exemptions" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Rhode Island should exempt all income from pensions and social security up to 200% of the federal poverty level from state income taxes. This would go a long way to ensuring retirement security for those who are the most in need. It would also bring greater parity between our tax code and popular retirement destination states, potentially decreasing the impulse to move to New Hampshire, North Carolina, and Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a progressive win. It’s a decrease in taxes that conservatives should like. It shouldn’t have a serious impact on revenues, especially if it goes a long way toward quelling the union and progressive rancor about the recent reforms. And it’s far from unprecedented– in fact, some form of retirement income tax exemption exists in virtually every other state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should not be proud of taking away our most vulnerable pensioners’ annual raises, even if it was necessary. Instead of ignoring the clear impact of this provision, my hope for 2013 is that we address it, while keeping an overall pretty good change to Rhode Island’s state retirement system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:worthy"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting, increases in food prices has largely slowed and the main driver of inflation are healthcare costs. I wonder to what extent Medicare/Medicaid and Obamacare shield retirees from rising healthcare costs&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:worthy" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:exemptions"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.ncsl.org/documents/fiscal/TaxonPensions2011.pdf&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:exemptions" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:raises"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/blog/2012/01/25/providence-pensions-lets-call-a-spade-a-spade-or-the-cola-a-raise/"&gt;Not a cost-of-living adjustment&lt;/a&gt;, or COLA, as some call them.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:raises" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Smarter Balance Released Items Scare Me</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2013/07/smarter-balance-released-items-scare-me.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason P. Becker</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2013-07-23:2013/07/smarter-balance-released-items-scare-me.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://ccssimath.blogspot.com/2013/06/our-sbac-practice-tests-run-through.html"&gt;CCSSI Mathematics&lt;/a&gt; posted a scathing look at the items released by the &lt;a href="http://www.smarterbalanced.org/"&gt;Smarter Balanced Assessment Consortium&lt;/a&gt; (SBAC). While the rest of the internet seems to be obsessed over &lt;a href="http://blogs.edweek.org/edweek/curriculum/2013/07/georgia_drops_out_of_parcc_tes.html"&gt;Georgia leaving the Partnership for Assessment of College and Careers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:absurdity"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:absurdity" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the real concern should be over the quality of these test items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although CCSSI also deligently point out questions that are not well aligned to the standards, this is the least of my worries. Adjusting the difficulty of items and better alignment is something that testing companies know how to do and deal with all the time. Computerized testing is the new ground and a big part of why states are, rightfully, excited about the consortium. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with the SBAC items is they represent the worst of computerized assessment. Rather than demonstrating more authentic and complex tasks, they present convoluted scenarios and even more convoluted input methods. Rather than present multimedia in a way that is authentic to the tasks, we see heavy language describing how to input what amounts to multiple choice or fill-in the blank answers. What I see here is not worth the investment in time and equipment that states are being asked to make, and it is hardly a "next generation" set of items that will allow us to attain more accurate measures of achievement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SBAC looks poised to set up students to fail because of the mechanations of test taking. This is not only tragic at face value, but assures an increase in test-prep as the items are less authentic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:absurdity"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of concern trolling over Georgia leaving PARCC by &lt;a href="http://www.edexcellence.net/commentary/education-gadfly-daily/flypaper/2013/thats-how-the-consortia-crumble.html"&gt;Andy Smarick on Twitter and Flypaper&lt;/a&gt;. I don't really see this as devastating, nor do I think some kind of supplication to the Tea Party could have changed this. Short of federal mandating of common tests and standards, Georgia was never going to stay aligned with a consortium that includes Massachusetts. Georgia has an incredibly inexpensive testing program, because they have built really poor assessments that are almost entirely multiple choice. They also have some of the &lt;a href="http://educationnext.org/despite-common-core-states-still-lack-common-standards/"&gt;lowest proficiency standards in the country&lt;/a&gt;. There was no way this state would move up to a testing regime that costs more than twice as much (but is around the country median) that is substantially more complex and will have a much higher standard for proficiency. Georgia is one of those states that clearly demonstrates some of the "soft bigotry of low expectations" by hiding behind inflated proficiency due to low standards.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:absurdity" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Economic Policy Institute is Wrong</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2013/06/economic-policy-institute-is-wrong.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason P. Becker</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2013-06-20:2013/06/economic-policy-institute-is-wrong.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.epi.org/"&gt;Economic Policy Institute&lt;/a&gt; has release a &lt;a href="http://www.epi.org/files/2013/ib366-rhode-islands-hybrid-pension-plan.pdf"&gt;short issue brief&lt;/a&gt; on the Rhode Island Retirement Security Act (RIRSA) by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rhiltnsmth"&gt;Robert Hiltonsmith&lt;/a&gt; that manages to get all of the details right but the big picture entirely wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EPI Issue Brief details the differences between the retirement system for state workers before and after the passage of RIRSA as accurately and clearly as I have ever seen. Mr. Hiltonsmith has done a notable job explaining the differences between the new system and the old system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brief, unfortunately, fails by engaging in two common fallacies to support its broader conclusions. The first is the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Straw_man"&gt;straw man fallacy&lt;/a&gt;. Mr. Hiltonsmith takes a limited set of the objectives of the entire RIRSA legislation and says defined contribution plans do not meet those objectives. That is true, but ignores the other objectives it does accomplish which were also part of the motivation behind RIRSA. The second is &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circular_reasoning"&gt;circular reasoning&lt;/a&gt;. In this case, Mr. Hiltonsmith states that the reason for a low funding ratio is because the state did not put 100% of its paper liability into the pension fund. This is a tautology and not in dispute and should not be trumpeted as a conclusion of analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are his three main points that he believes makes RIRSA a bad policy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The defined contribution plan does not save the state money from its annual pension contributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The defined contribution plan is likely to earn lower returns and therefore result in lower benefits for retirees.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The defined contribution plan does not solve the low funding ratio of the pension plan which exists because law makers did not make required contributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the defined contribution portion of RIRSA was not in place to do any of these three things. The purpose of including a defined contribution plan in the new state pension system is to create stability in annual budget allocations and avoid locking the government into promises it has demonstrated it fails to keep. Defined benefit plans require the state to change pension contributions when there are market fluctuations and leads to anti-cyclical costs, where the state is forced to put substantially more resources into pensions when revenues are lowest and spending on social welfare is most important. The defined contribution plan keeps the payments required by the state consistent and highly predictable. This is far preferable from a budget perspective. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that there are lower returns to defined contribution plans which may lead to a decrease in overall benefits. It is my opinion that the unions in Rhode Island should be pushing for a substantially better match on the defined contribution portion of their plan that more closely resembles private sector match rates. This could more than alleviate the difference in benefits while maintaining the predictability, for budgeting purposes, of the defined contribution plan. I doubt this policy would have much hope of passing while Rhode Island slowly crawls out of a deep recession, but it is certainly a reasonable matter for future legislatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are only two ways to decrease the current pension fund shortfalls: increase payments to the fund or decrease benefits. There is no structural magic sauce to get around this. Structural changes in the pension system are aimed at reducing the likelihood that the state will reproduce its current situation, with liabilities well outstripping funds. It is true that the "savings" largely came from cutting benefits. I have not heard anyone claim otherwise. The only alternative was to put a big lump sum into the pension fund. That clearly was not a part of RIRSA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is absurd to judge RIRSA on the ability of defined contribution plans to achieve policy objectives that are unrelated to the purpose of this structural change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most troubling conclusion of this brief was that, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shortfall in Rhode Island’s pension plan for public employees is largely due not to overly generous benefits, but to the failure of state and local government employers to pay their required share of pensions’ cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read that and expected to see evidence of skipped payments or a discussion of overly ambitious expectations for investment returns, etc. Instead, it seems that this conclusion is based simply on the fact that the benefits in Rhode Island were not deemed outrageously large, and therefore Rhode Island should just pay the liability hole. The "failure" here is predicated entirely on the idea that the pensions as offered should be met, period, whatever the cost to the government. This is the "required share". Which, of course, is technically true without a change in the law, but feels disingenuous. It is essentially a wholesale agreement with the union interpretation of the state pension system as an immutable contract. The courts will likely resolve whether or not this is true. My objection is that Mr. Hiltonsmith makes a definitive statement on this rationale without describing it. In such a lucid description of how the retirement system has changed, it seems this could only be intentional omission intended to support a predetermined conclusion rather than illuminate the unconvinced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Hiltonsmith also claims that, "Over the long term, RIRSA may cost the state upwards of $15 million a year in additional contributions while providing a smaller benefit for the average full-career worker." I am not 100% certain, but based on his use of the normal cost &lt;sup id="fnref:normal cost"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:normal cost" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to do these calculations, it appears this conclusion is drawn only based on the marginal contributions to current employees. In other words, if we &lt;em&gt;completely ignore&lt;/em&gt; the existing liability, the new plan cost the state more money marginally while potentially decreasing benefits for employees. It is my opinion that Mr. Hiltonsmith is intentionally creating the perception that RIRSA costs more than the current plan while providing fewer benefits. Again, this is true for future liabilities, but ignores that RIRSA also dramatically decreased the unfunded liabilities through cutting existing retiree benefits. So the overall cost for the act is far less, while the marginal cost was increased with the objective of decreasing the instability in government appropriations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can have a serious debate about whether there is value in the state goals of a defined contribution plan. In my view, the purpose of switching to this structure is about: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portability of plans for more mobile workers, potentially serving to attract younger and more highly skilled employees. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stability in government expenditures on retiree benefits from year to year that are less susceptible to market forces. This includes avoiding the temptation to reduce payments when there are strong market returns as well as the crushing difficulty of increasing payments when the market (and almost certainly government receipts) are down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insulating workers from a government that perpetually writes checks they can cash, as was the case with the current system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper does not address any of these objectives or others I might have forgotten. In essence, the brief looks at only one subset of the perceived costs of this structural change, but it is far from a comprehensive analysis of the potential universe of both costs and benefits. In fact, it fails to even address the most commonly cited benefits. That is why I view it as heavily biased and flawed, even if I might draw similar conclusions from a more thorough analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:normal cost"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definition: Active participants earn new benefits each year. Actuaries call that the normal cost. The normal cost is always reflected in the cash and accounting cost of the plan. &lt;a href="http://www.actuary.org/pdf/pension/fundamentals_0704.pdf"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; In other words, the normal cost only looks at the new benefits added to the liability, not the existing liability.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:normal cost" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Calculating Age in R</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2013/06/calculating-age-in-r.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason P. Becker</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2013-06-12:2013/06/calculating-age-in-r.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few months back I wrote some code to calculate age from a date of birth and arbitrary end date. It is not a real tricky task, but it is certainly one that comes up often when doing research on individual-level data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a bit surprised to only find bits and pieces of code and advice on how to best go about this task. After reading through some old R-help and Stack Overflow responses on various ways to do date math in R, this is the function I wrote &lt;sup id="fnref:wrote"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:wrote" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;age_calc &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;dob&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; enddate&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;Sys.Date&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; units&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;months&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="kr"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;inherits&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;dob&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Date&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;inherits&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;enddate&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Date&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    stop&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Both dob and enddate must be Date class objects&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  start &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; as.POSIXlt&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;dob&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  end &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; as.POSIXlt&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;enddate&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

  years &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; end&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;year &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; start&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;year
  &lt;span class="kr"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;units&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;years&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    result &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; ifelse&lt;span class="p"&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;end&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mon &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; start&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mon&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; 
                      &lt;span class="p"&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;end&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mon &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; start&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mon&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;end&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mday &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; start&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mday&lt;span class="p"&gt;)),&lt;/span&gt;
                      years &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; years&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;    
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;units&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;months&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    months &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;years&lt;span class="m"&gt;-1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;
    result &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; months &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; start&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mon
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;units&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;days&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    result &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; difftime&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;end&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; start&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; units&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;days&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    stop&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Unrecognized units. Please choose years, months, or days.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="kr"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;result&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A few notes on proper usage and the choices I made in writing this function: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The parameters &lt;code&gt;dob&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;enddate&lt;/code&gt; expect data that is already in one of the various classes that minimally inherits the base class &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This function takes advantage of the way that R treats vectors, so both &lt;code&gt;dob&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;enddate&lt;/code&gt; can be a single or multi-element vector. For example &lt;code&gt;enddate&lt;/code&gt; is a single date, as is the default, then the function will return a vector that calculates the difference between &lt;code&gt;dob&lt;/code&gt; and that single date for each element in &lt;code&gt;dob&lt;/code&gt;. If &lt;code&gt;dob&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;enddate&lt;/code&gt; are both vectors with n&amp;gt;1, then the returned vector will contain the &lt;a href="http://heather.cs.ucdavis.edu/~matloff/r.old.html#elementwise"&gt;element-wise&lt;/a&gt; difference between &lt;code&gt;dob&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;enddate&lt;/code&gt;. When the vectors are of different sizes, the shorter vector will be repeated over until it reaches the same length as the longer vector. This is known as &lt;a href="http://cran.r-project.org/doc/manuals/R-intro.html#The-recycling-rule"&gt;recycling&lt;/a&gt;, and it is the default behavior in R.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This function always returns an integer. Calculating age in years will never return, say, 26.2. Instead, it assumes that the correct behavior for age calculations is something like a &lt;code&gt;floor&lt;/code&gt; function. For examle, the function will only return 27 if &lt;code&gt;enddate&lt;/code&gt; is minimally your 27th birthday. Up until that day you are considered 26. The same is true for age in months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably the first custom function in almost 3 years using R that I wrote to be truly generalizable. I was inspired by three factors. First, this is a truly frequent task that I will have to apply to many data sets in the future that I don't want to have to revisit. Second, a professional acquaintance, &lt;a href="http://jaredknowles.com/"&gt;Jared Knowles&lt;/a&gt;, is putting together a CRAN package with various convenience functions for folks who are new to R and using it to analyze education data &lt;sup id="fnref:eeptools"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:eeptools" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This seemed like an appropriate addition to that package, so I wanted to write it to that standard. In fact, it was my first (and to date, only) submitted and accepted pull request on Github. Third, it is a tiny, simple function so it was easy to wrap my head around and write it well. I will let you be the judge of my success or failure &lt;sup id="fnref:inspiration"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:inspiration" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:wrote"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I originally used &lt;code&gt;Sys.time()&lt;/code&gt; not realizing there was a &lt;code&gt;Sys.Date()&lt;/code&gt; function. Thanks to Jared Knowles for that edit in preparation for a CRAN check.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:wrote" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:eeptools"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href="https://github.com/jknowles/eeptools"&gt;eeptools&lt;/a&gt; on Github.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:eeptools" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:inspiration"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="http://mcfromnz.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/updated-age-calculation-function/"&gt;Matt's Stats n Stuff&lt;/a&gt; for getting me to write this post. When I saw another age calculation function pop up on the r-bloggers feed I immediately thought of this function. Matt pointed out that it was quite hard to Google for age calculations in R, lamenting that Google doesn't meaningfully crawl Github where I linked to find my code. So this post is mostly about providing some help to less experience R folks who are frantically Googling as both Matt and I did when faced with this need.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:inspiration" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Linear Thinking</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2013/06/linear-thinking.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason P. Becker</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2013-06-02:2013/06/linear-thinking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Apple will be revealing new details for both of its major operating systems at WWDC on June 10, 2013. The focus of much speculation has been how Apple will improve multi-tasking and inter-app communication in iOS7. As batteries have grown, CPUs have become increasingly powerful, and the application &lt;a href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2012/11/frictionless.html"&gt;ecosystem&lt;/a&gt; has matured &lt;sup id="fnref:viticci"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:viticci" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the iOS sandboxing model has felt increasingly limiting and outdated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that there is a simple change that could dramatically increase the effectiveness of multitasking on iOS by re-examining how application switching works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrolling through a long list of applications, either through the basement shelf or via the four-finger gesture on an iPad, is both slow and lacking in contextual cues. In a simple case where I am working with two applications simultaneously, how do I switch between them? The list of open applications always places the current application in the first position. The previously used application sits in the second position. The first time I want to change to another application this is not so bad. I move to the "right" on the list to progress forward into the next application &lt;sup id="fnref:next"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:next" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble comes when I want to return to where I was just working. The most natural mental model for this switch is to move "left" in the list. I moved "right" to get here and millions of years of evolution has taught me the the "undo button" for moving right is to move left &lt;sup id="fnref:inform7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:inform7" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But of course, when I attempt to move "left", I find no destination &lt;sup id="fnref:youcant"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:youcant" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I can pop an application from anywhere on the list, but I can only prepend new applications to the list &lt;sup id="fnref:ignorant"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:ignorant" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple needs to move away from its linear thinking and enter the second dimension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if I could drag apps in the switcher on top of each other to make a new stack, not unlike the option on the OS X launch bar? Throughout this stack, position is maintained regardless of which application is in use/was last used. I can always move &lt;strong&gt;up&lt;/strong&gt; from Chrome to ByWord, and &lt;strong&gt;down&lt;/strong&gt; to Good Reader, for example, if I was writing a report. Apple might call this a Stack, mirroring the term in OSX, but I would prefer this to be called a &lt;em&gt;Flow&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this feature is to organize a &lt;em&gt;Flow&lt;/em&gt; for a particular task that requires using multiple apps. One feature might be saving a "Flow", this way each time I want to write a blog post, I tap the same home screen button and the same four apps in the same order launch in a &lt;em&gt;Flow&lt;/em&gt;, ready for easy switching using the familiar four-finger swipe gesture up and down. I no longer have to worry about the sequence I have recently accessed applications which is confusing and requires me to look at the app switcher draw or needlessly and repeatedly swipe through applications. I never have to worry about lingering too long on one application while swiping through and switching to that app, changing my position to the origin of the list and starting over again. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all the calls for complex inter-app communication or having multiple apps active on the screen at the same time, it seems a simple interface change to application switching could complete change the way we multitask on iOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:viticci"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Federico Viticci has either shown us the light or gone completely mad.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:viticci" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:next"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, lets assume the right application is next in the stack. I'll get to that issue with my second change.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:next" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:inform7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;You are in a green room. &amp;gt; Go east. You are in a red room. &amp;gt; Go west. You are in a green room.&lt;/code&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:inform7" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:youcant"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;You can't go that way.&lt;/code&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:youcant" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:ignorant"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know enough about data structures yet to name what's going on here. I am tempted to think that the challenge is they have presented a list to users, with a decidedly horizontal metaphor, when they actually have created something more akin to a stack, with a decidedly vertical metaphor. But a stack isn't quite the right way to understand the app switcher. You can "pop" an app from any arbitrary position on the app switcher, but funny enough can only push a new app on to the top of the switcher.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:ignorant" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Cleaning URLs with TextExpander</title><link href="http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2013/05/cleaning-urls-with-textexpander.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason P. Becker</name></author><id>tag:blog.jsonbecker.com,2013-05-30:2013/05/cleaning-urls-with-textexpander.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One thing I really dislike about Google Reader is it replaces the links to posts in my RSS feed. My &lt;a href="http://pinboard.in/u:jasonpbecker"&gt;Pinboard account&lt;/a&gt; is littered with links that start with &lt;code&gt;http://feedproxy.google.com&lt;/code&gt;. I am quite concerned that with the demise of &lt;a href="http://googlereader.blogspot.com/2013/03/powering-down-google-reader.html"&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt; on July 1, 2013, these redirects will no longer work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not just Google that obscures the actually address of links on the internet. The popularity of using link shortening services, both to save characters on Twitter and to collect analytics, has proliferated the &lt;em&gt;Internet of Redirects&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worse still, after I am done cutting through redirects, I often find that the ultimate link include all kinds of extraneous attributes, most especially a barrage of &lt;code&gt;utm_*&lt;/code&gt; campaign tracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I understand why all of this is happening and the importance of the services and analytics this link cruft provides. I am quite happy to click on shortened links, move through all the redirects, and let sites know just how I found them. But quite often, like when using a bookmarking service or writing a blog post, I just want the simple, plain text URL that gets me directly to the permanent home of the content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One part of my workflow to deal with link cruft is a TextExpander snippet I call &lt;code&gt;cleanURL&lt;/code&gt;. It triggers a simple Python script that grabs the URL in my clipboard, traces through the redirects to the final destination, then strips links of campaign tracking attributes, and ultimately pastes a new URL that is much "cleaner".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below I have provided the script. I hope it is useful to some other folks, and I would love some recommendations for additional "cleaning" that could be performed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next task is expanding this script to work with &lt;a href="http://pinboard.in"&gt;Pinboard&lt;/a&gt; so that I can clean up all my links before the end of the month when Google Reader goes belly up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;#!/usr/bin/python&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;requests&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;re&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;search&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;check_output&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;check_output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;pbpaste&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c"&gt;# Go through the redirects to get the destination URL&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;requests&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c"&gt;# Look for utm attributes&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;match&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="n"&gt;search&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;r&amp;#39;[?&amp;amp;#]utm_&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c"&gt;# Because I&amp;#39;m not smart and trigger this with&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c"&gt;# already clean URLs&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;match&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;cleanURL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;match&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;group&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;cleanURL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cleanURL&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry></feed>